<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A defence of the true church called Quakers (come and coming out of the wilderness, Babylon, and the dark night of the apostacy of Antichrist into their own land, which is Sion the mountain of holiness, there to worship the Lord in spirit and truth) against the several sects and sorts of people, called Independants, Separatists or Brownists, Baptists, Fift-Monarchy-Men ...</title>
            <author>Crook, John, 1617-1699.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 135 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35122</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C7202</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R35612</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15491468</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15491468</idno>
            <idno type="VID">103574</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35122)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 103574)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1186:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A defence of the true church called Quakers (come and coming out of the wilderness, Babylon, and the dark night of the apostacy of Antichrist into their own land, which is Sion the mountain of holiness, there to worship the Lord in spirit and truth) against the several sects and sorts of people, called Independants, Separatists or Brownists, Baptists, Fift-Monarchy-Men ...</title>
                  <author>Crook, John, 1617-1699.</author>
                  <author>J. C. (John Collens), d. 1682.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>56 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Simmons ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Occasionally attributed to John Collens.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:103574:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:103574:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DEFENCE OF THE True Church Called QUAKERS,</p>
            <p>(Come and coming out of the Wilderneſſe, Babylon, and the dark Night of the Apoſtacy of Antichriſt into their own Land, which is <hi>Sion</hi> the Mountain of Holineſſe, there to Worſhip the Lord in Spirit and Truth) againſt the ſeveral Sects and ſorts of people, called <hi>Independants, Separatiſts</hi> or <hi>Browniſts, Baptiſts, Fift Monarchy-men, Seekers,</hi> and <hi>High No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioniſts</hi> of all ſorts, who by the True Light are found and diſcovered to be out of the ſame.</p>
            <p>Written by <hi>J. C.</hi> According to the meaſure of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom given unto him from God, who is the giver of every good gift.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Simmons</hi> at the <hi>Bull</hi> and <hi>Mouth</hi> near <hi>Alderſgate,</hi> 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:103574:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:103574:2"/>
            <p>WHen the <hi>Jewes</hi> outward Returned from the Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity of <hi>Babylon,</hi> which was the true figure of the Saints coming out of the long and dark night of Apoſtacy, from the Doctrine and Life of the Apoſtles in the Primitive Times, which was the Captivity of the ſpiritual Seed, ſo great and many were their Enemies who endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to cauſe their Work (in repairing the deſolate and ruined places of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>) to ceaſe, that thoſe who were imployed in that Work, with one hand wrought, and with the other held the Weapon; even ſo is it and muſt it be now at the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn of the ſpiritual Seed, not only within, by exerciſing Faith and Prayer upon and to him that is able to ſave to the uttermoſt, and in his ſtrength wreſtling againſt the Dragon and his Angels, Principalities, Powers, and Spiritual Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes in High Places, and ſundry temptations, ſo quenching by the Armour of Light all the fiery Darts of the wicked one; but alſo <hi>without,</hi> both by holding forth the Word of their teſtimony, and ſealing it with their bloud and ſufferings for the conviction and converſion of ſinners, ſo fitting ſtones for Gods ſpiritual building, and alſo by ſtopping the mouths of gain-ſayers, who ſhall not be able to reſiſt the Spirit by which they ſpeak; So ſtanding in the gap and quitting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves like Spiritual-men againſt the Beaſt and falſe Prophet, and all the Armies of the Aliens.</p>
            <p>Hear now therefore all ye that are called <hi>Independants, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratiſts,</hi> or <hi>Browniſts, Baptiſts, Fift Monarchy-men, Seekers,</hi> high <hi>Notioniſts</hi> of all ſorts, the <hi>Apologie</hi> or <hi>Defence</hi> that I in the wiſdom and ſtrength of my God (for without him I can do nothing) do make againſt you, and for the true Church called <hi>Quakers,</hi> againſt whom and whoſe ſtanding Profeſſion ye variouſly have prejudice and do contend.</p>
            <p>And Firſt for you called <hi>Independants,</hi> ye aſſume a great Name, but ye are not found in the <hi>Independant</hi> nature, and ſo are not the true Church; for although ye profeſſe your ſelves as to the viſible Adminiſtration of Church-power, not to have dependance upon other Congregations or Churches
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:103574:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> as an inferiour on a ſuperiour; yet are there many things ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parently ſeen amongſt you which do un-Church you and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move your Candleſtick far off; for the true golden Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks among whom Chriſt the Son of God walketh, do hold up and hold forth the true light that it may ſhine before men; but ye (as do the common multitude) reject it, ſleight it, and Diſpute againſt it as invalid and inſufficient to lead in the way everlaſting; and ſo ye would have it kept under the buſhel, yea, quite extinguiſhed in the hearts of men, and would have the Scriptures or Writings to be a light to it, and not it an enlightener and opener of them, whereby ye ſtumble at the Scriptures themſelves, and cannot diſcern of the times and ſeaſons, or of the Saints ſeveral ſtates and conditions to God-ward, who becauſe they ſometime witneſſed a war and ſtriving againſt the body of ſin, therefore ſay you, they muſt alway while they live carry it about them, as though the Saints fought as thoſe that beat the Air, or as though their labour were in vain in the Lord: Oh! fooliſh people and unwiſe, when will ye come to the true Teacher in your ſelves, that ye may believe and know the Promiſe made unto the ſeed, <hi>That there ſhall be no more a pricking Bryar unto the Houſe of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>nor a grieving Thorn of all that are round about them that deſpiſe them; and they ſhall know that I am the Lord: Alſo that their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies which they have ſeen to day, they ſhall ſee them again no more for ever:</hi> And that ye may ſee their intereſt in Chriſts Prayer (whom the Father heard alwayes, becauſe he did alwayes the things that pleaſed him) who ſaid, <hi>Neither Pray I; for theſe alone</hi> (to wit, for the Apoſtles and Saints then in the world, that they might be ſanctified through the Truth) <hi>but for them alſo who ſhall believe in me through their words, that they all may be one, &amp;c. I in them and thou in me, that hey may be made perfect in one, and that the world may know that thou haſt ſent me, and haſt loved them as thou haſt loved me.</hi> Mark, This was a ſtate of Saints Perfection in this world, that worldly Spirits might be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced thereby; but ye being in the unbelief, are (even as the multitude) alwayes hanging upon the lips of men, whoſe tongues are not touched (as the Prophets was) with a Coal from Gods Altar, who witneſſed his ſin purged, and ſo are ever learning, and never come to the true knowledge; for
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:103574:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> the Paſtors and Teachers of your Congregations have not yet witneſſed the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rim</hi> of the Sanctuary, I mean the true ſpiritual Gift, by believing and waiting on the true light which ſhineth in their dark hearts, that ſhould give them power from on high to miniſter in, but are either men learned with the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this world, or ſuch who through ſtrength of Brain, and often reading of the Letter of the Scriptures, can com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a Form of Words and deliver it unto you after a Prieſtly manner; ſo that ye (as ſtill unſatisfied) heap to your ſelves National Prieſts alſo for Teachers, ſometimes hearing the one, and ſometimes the other; Yea, ſome of your Paſtors (ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led) are National Prieſts alſo: Oh! (Friends,) it might ſhame you and make you bluſh for ſhame (if ye could rightly conſider) to call your ſelves the Churches of Chriſt, and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependants,</hi> and be thus ſo dependant on mans Teachings; Yea, joyning with the National Prieſts about the way of ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding out a Miniſtrie, and bearing the Beaſts very Mark in your Foreheads while ye are ſo called; owning your Baptiſm in your Infancie to be true, though miniſtred to a blank, and by thoſe who ſprang from a Popiſh ſtock, and ſprinkling your own Infants now from a falſe apprehenſion of the Promiſe made to you and your ſeed after the fleſh, ſo calling that the ſeed; whereas the true Churches of Chriſt knew no ſuch ſeed, nor owned any, but that which ſprang out of Chriſts womb in the Regeneration, who is a quickning Spirit: So Chriſt the Corner-ſtone and Head of the Church, even the true and univerſal Light is come to fight againſt you with the ſword of his mouth, and to teſtifie to your faces, <hi>That though ye call your ſelves Jewes, yet ye are not, but do lye:</hi> Yea, your Converſation in the world moſt plainly ſheweth that your ſpot is not the ſpot of his Children; for we ſee you ſo mingled and interwoven in the Pride, Covetouſneſs, Policie and Folly of the world, that we could not by any holy walking know you, or cull you out as the clean from the unclean, or as Sheep from the midſt of the Goats, if we did not now and then hear ſome of you called <hi>Independants;</hi> Lord, how emptie a thing it is to have a Name to live and to be dead? Wherefore come to him who is the Reſurrection and the life, which life is the light of men, and becometh the light of life to all that believe and wait in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:103574:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> it, that they may bring forth fruit unto God, and ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come living ſtones built up a ſpiritual Houſe; for this is the Church of the Firſt-born, whoſe Names are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in Heaven: For what is it for people to cry, <hi>The Temple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lord, The Church of Chriſt,</hi> the Church of Chriſt, and to be polluted and unclean both in Worſhip and Practice, or to call themſelves the Children of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and not to do the Works of <hi>Abraham,</hi> for he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſook the Idolatry of his Fathers Houſe, and in obedience to the Lords call, came into a Land that he ſhewed him; ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to the Croſs to his own will, he alſo ſaw Chriſts day and was glad, and walked before the Lord and was upright, but ye do neither of theſe, as being ſtill in the abominations of the Whore, who have made the Nations drunk, as kicking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the prick, the True Light and Reprover for ſin and evil, and living in the Deteſtable Waies, Cuſtoms and Faſhions of the World; ſo the Sun-ſhine of the Light in this the day of the Lords Power hath put and is putting out your Candle in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcuritie, &amp; hath removed your Candleſtick becauſe ye repented not; for he hath raiſed up a People at laſt in this Nation wherein he hath placed his Name that it might not fall in the ſtreets; who as they are faithful to the firſt Principle of God in them, to wit the Light, ſhall out-live, out-ſhine and eat out the Heart and Soul of all Profeſſors and profeſſions in the World that are found in the Idolatry, Pride and Vanity thereof, though under great and fair pretences of Chriſtian Religion, which ſtands not in high words, but in loving Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, doing Juſtice, and walking humbly with the Lord God; ſo every way and in every thing keeping themſelves unſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of the World, yea hating even the garment ſpotted with the fleſh.</p>
            <p>So that neither can ye <hi>Browniſts</hi> or <hi>Separatiſts</hi> in this the Lords day, eſcape his Righteous Judgement and cenſure, though ye ſeem to ſtand at a greater diſtance from falſe Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip then the <hi>Independents</hi> do, but being weighed in the equal ballance are found too light to be accounted by us for the True Church of Chriſt; yet I Know that becauſe it is ſaid in the Scripture, <hi>come out from among them and be ye ſeparate,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>and touch no unclean thing and I will receive you, &amp;c.</hi> ye are
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:103574:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> very confident of your ſtanding, for ye ſay, <hi>ye are ſeparated from the National Antichriſtian Worſhip, abhorring their Idol Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and will not hear any of their Baals Prieſts, or break any Bread with them, &amp;c.</hi> But conſider impa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>lly whether ye touch no unclean thing, yea whether ye came not from them with their grand abomination in your boſoms, which ye have ever ſince foſtered and practiſed, and that with (a ſeeming) no little zeal, I mean the Sprinkling or Baptizing of your Infants, upon the account of their being the Seed of the Covenant as they are your Children, who ſay, <hi>ye are believers,</hi> a moſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiching Sorcerie this is, and an exceeding betrayer of the Pure Life of God, and that which bears death in the very face of it, and if ye are true to your own Principles, ye muſt needs be ſoon un-churched hereby, and brought back to <hi>Babylon</hi> do what you can, for your Children being hereby made Viſible Members of your Body, they muſt needs be accounted Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren as they grow up in years amongſt you, though Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration be not witneſſed by them (for by your own Approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Act ye received them in before they knew their very right Hand from their left) and ſo they muſt have all the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veledges of Brethren, though not diſcerning the Lords Body, or able to ſeparate between the Precious and the Vile, or not ſavouring the things of the Spirit of God as the Natural man doth not, whereby a confuſed medly and mixt multitude muſt needs appear, yea and the tares ſoon overſpread, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grow, and overtop the Wheat if there be any; and ſo that which ye counted the Churches of Chriſt, plainly be come, and be ſeen to be by thoſe in the Light, but the Field which is the World; is not this to mock God, and to throw down with one hand what ye would ſet up with the other? Come to the Light of Chriſt in your Conſciences which makes manifeſt all things, and let True Judgement proceed; But alas ye are as great Enemies to that Pure Principle of God, which ſhould reprove you for all deceitful and confuſed actings, and give you a right diſcerning, and purge you from all ſin, as any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther whatſoever, and are ſo rivited on the letter without, that ye will not endure to hear of the True Light within, <hi>which enlighteneth every man that cometh into the World,</hi> without which no mans heart could be ſearched, or ever any man converted
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:103574:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> to God. For I would know of you <hi>Separatiſts,</hi> how any of you at firſt came to be troubled for ſin, or to have any good deſires begotten in you towards the Lord or his Truth, which ye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to know and w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> willing to ſuffer for? was not this done by the Spirit of the Lord which moved and ſtirred in you? and whence came this convincing and illuminating Spirit? came it from above the clouds, or pierced it into you from without? or was the thing alwayes within you, ſtriving and ſtrugling at ſeveral times, though ye took little notice of it before ye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be humbled by it? can any man (even while unregene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate) flee any more from Gods preſence and Spirit, that his hand ſhould not find him out, then after Regeneration? or could <hi>David</hi> have done ſo before converſion more then after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards? can the wicked hide themſelves that the Lord ſhould not ſee them any more then the godly? I believe ye will all anſwer Nay; and if ſo, is the Spirit of the Lord God (who filleth all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and things with its preſence,) out of a wicked man, or at a greater diſtance (as to place) from him then from a Righteous Man, though in the manner of its operation in them I know it is different, judging and repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the one, and comforting and encouraging the other; So then the Spirit or Life being in and nigh every one, the true light muſt needs be in every one, for the life is the light of men, and ſo whatever good thing is wrought in mans heart, doth not come from without him, or from far, but from the word within the mouth and heart, and ſo ariſeth from within himſelf; for ſaith wiſdom, a good man ſhall be ſatisfied from himſelf; and ſo did Chriſt promiſe, <hi>Whoſoever,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>drinketh of the water that I ſhall give him, ſhall never thirſt, but it ſhall be a Well of waters ſpringing up in him to Eternal Life;</hi> and ſo did <hi>Iſaiah</hi> Propheſie, <hi>As the Earth bringeth forth her bud, and as the Garden cauſeth the things that are ſown in it to ſpring forth, ſo the Lord God will cauſe righteouſneſs and praiſe to ſpring forth before all the Nations;</hi> Oh! the ſweet ſpringings and bud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of the pure Life of God in mans heart, after a night and winter of ſorrow and darkneſs, and ſilent waiting upon that of God in him; ſurely by this means and no other ſhall Righteouſneſs towards man, and praiſe and glory to the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:103574:5"/> Lord God who is worthy, and alone worthy, ſpring up in the ſight of others.</p>
            <p>And oh! ye <hi>Separatiſts,</hi> ſo called, how can it be expected that ye ſhould Miniſter to each other in your Aſſemblies by the living Power of the Spirit of truth (which is the Holy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointing, and the onely Exerciſer of the Saints in all their adminiſtrations) any more than others do, but that ye ſhould be as dead, dry and formal as they in ſuch exerciſes, when as ye will not turn to the light which is the true Teacher, and in the humility and penitency of your ſpirits wait in ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence for the Comforters preſence; are ye not now compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended and diſcerned by (thoſe who walk in the light as he is in the light) to be dry, dead and unſavoury, and hating re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof and your Reprover, who now calls for more living fruit in this his day of light and truth than in the times of more ignorance? And are ye not proud and covetous, and ſet down at eaſe in the wayes and cuſtoms of men, as reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting perſons, &amp;c. as if there were no more croſs to be taken up, when the greateſt is yet behind? For the light ſhining in your dark hearts, as it ariſeth, will croſs your own wills and wiſdom exceedingly, and reject your vain confidence of your being the onely true Church, and ſo ye will appear na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and bare, as thoſe that have been but in a dream, that ye were come out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> when as the Whore and Beaſts mark is diſcerned in your foreheads, &amp; other of her trumpery among you; Wherefore I exhort you in Gods love and fear to come unto the light within, which brings out of death and deadneſs and all tranſgreſſion, and out of all the wayes of confuſion, and that abominable practiſe of Infant Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm which is a chief ground thereof; and be not deceived, God is not mocked, for ſuch as ye ſow ye ſhall reap, and if ye will ſtill ſow to the fleſh as ye have a long time done, ye ſhall reap cor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uption, vanity and ſorrow; but if ye will ſow to the Spirit, and lay your ground work there, ye ſhall from thence certainly reap life Everlaſting.</p>
            <p>But what hath he againſt us and our Profeſſion may the B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts ſay, who have not onely renounced ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Infant Baptiſme as a groſs deceit, but have practiſed in direct oppo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ition there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to by being dipped or baptized in water, and ſo profeſs Faith
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:103574:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> and Baptiſm as the Apoſtles &amp; Saints did before the Apoſtacy?</p>
            <p>The Spirit of the Lord hath enough againſt your Faith, for ſome of you are for Free Will, which ye ſay is a power placed in you, whereby ye are able to ſtand or fall to your own Maſter of your own accord, by taking heed to what the Scriptures outwardly declare, ſome part whereof you call the Goſpel, and own no other, ſo that one of ye once de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, <hi>He knew no other Spirit now than the Scriptures;</hi> as if the Spirit that moved the holy men of God to ſpeak forth the Scriptures, when it had ſo moved them, had done its work, and ſo quite forſaken the Earth; when as the greateſt glory of the Church, and pureſt life of the Saints is to be brought forth in theſe laſt times, as the Propheſies of the Scriptures do plentifully fore-ſhew, which cannot be brought to paſs but by the Spirit of the living God, which Spirit or Life is but one in all and in all ages, which is a ſpirit of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and burning, whoſe pure Judgements and Holy burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings are felt in this day of the Lords winnowing by thoſe, who every one in their own meaſure and order do ſilently, ſincerely and humbly wait for the ſame; for although we ſay that every ones condemnation is juſt for loving his evil deeds, and hating the light that ſhines in his heart, yet no man is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in his own will, diſtinct from this light, to adde one cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit unto his ſtature, that is, to make one ſtep in ſaving know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge or obedience, but is to believe in the light, and wait therein, ſo tarrying the Lords leaſure, till he ariſe in him up to the prey, leading captivity c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ptive, and bri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ging forth Judgement unto victory; and if this ſeems a ſtrange or fooliſh Language unto you, know that it is becauſe ye are in your own wills, in diſtinction from the light, which is Gods faithful witneſs within you, which faithful witneſs is Chriſt the Power of God unto Salvation unto every one that believeth, &amp; this is the Goſpel or glad tidings indeed, that man is not left to himſelf to work out his own Salvation, but that the God of all grace hath left in him a ſeed (which) as a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation thereof was plentifully manifeſted in his Son made of a woman in due time, in which he believing that it ſhould break the ſerpents head, and do all his works in him and for him; ſo that ye Free-willers (ſo called) ſtumbling at this ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling-ſtone,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:103574:6"/> and ſetting up the Scriptures (which are but a wholſom Declaration of this ſeed and corner-ſtone) in its place; I do Declare againſt you and all ſuch, that ye are Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters, and ſo out of the true Faith of Gods Elect, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not the true Church of Chriſt, but the ſynagogue of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan. Wherefore I exhort you to come out of your own wills and carnal wiſdom, which begets you in your Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations into many vain janglings, rents and diſputings; and to wait in ſilence upon the Reprover in you for ſin (which alone is able to give you victory over ſin) that your mouths may be for ever ſtopped for pleading againſt the true light, which is the true Prophet, that ye periſh not in the gain-ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Kore,</hi> who alſo ſtood up againſt the Lords Prophet. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers deny indeed mans power, will and ability to do good, and ſo deny you, as out of the Faith; but how (ſince they are become ſuch diſputers againſt, and denyers of the true light that lightneth every man) they ſhould themſelves be in the true Faith, or find power and ability to bring forth any good and acceptable fruit unto God, I cannot behold; for which way ſhould ye feel his living Power to enable you thereunto, or which way ſhould the Spirit of the Lord come? Do you look for him by way of local motion, and ſo to enter from without to within you, can ſuch a thought be without ſetting the phanſie on work, and ſo making an Image of the Godhead within your ſelves; but if ye will not be accounted I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolaters, then muſt you needs come to the light within, which muſt reveal unto you the Image of the Inviſible God in the ſtill ſilence, and that which can reveal the Fathers Glory, muſt moſt certainly diſcover ſin and evil which vails the ſame (while undiſcovered and unjudged down and deſtroyed) from the mind of man; but this alſo ye Baptized Perſons (that ſay ye deny mans Free Will) cannot believe, for ye think and ſay, though ſin do remain in you (as it muſt as long as ye live here) yet ye have an Advocate with the Father, and ſo are juſtified by Chriſts Merits and Righteouſneſs, the which for any one to deny, ye account a denial of Free Grace, yea and of Chriſt himſelf; So ye think ye may behold the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Preſence even while ſin is ſtanding. Alas, alas Friends, ye are much deceived (as are the common multitude) herein;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:103574:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> for in this day of Chriſt (the true light) another kind of Free Grace, and another manner of Saviour is diſcovered and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed, than hath been formerly imagined; for know ye, that Gods Free Grace is his Free Gift in giving his Son a light in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world, whereby as men come to ſee, confeſs and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake all evil in thought, word and deed, Juſtification, Reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation and Peace with the Lord God they may come to witneſſe, and no otherwiſe; for whoſoever hath at any time ſeen his pure ſhape with a ſpiritual eye, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gine or deſire to have theſe any other way, his pure eyes beholding no Iniquity in any one without reproof where ever he finds it, neither can his all-ſeeing eye but ſee it where ever it is, and this is alſo the Saviour that we believe in and Preach, and no other, to wit a Chriſt to be known within, manifeſted in our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eſh to deſtroy the works of the Devil, ſo ſaving us from the wrath to come, for he was not at all ſent to juſtifie or ſave his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in their ſins but from their ſins, ſo is judgement laid to the line and equity to the plummet; look how far judgement hath paſſed upon the tranſgreſſour in any one, ſo far is mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy witneſſed by the tranſgreſſour and no farther, and it is equity that it ſhould be ſo, yet is it moſt free grace, in that the Lord God Almighty freely ſaves in this righteous way, by his own Almighty Arm, but ſo as that the creature may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member and take notice, <hi>that if the righteous ſcarcely be ſaved, where ſhall the wicked and ungodly appear?</hi> neither would this (Doctrine oh ye Baptiſts) ſeem a hard ſaying unto you, if ye were not double-minded, loving the Lords Salvation and your ſins alſo, to wit, pride, covetouſneſs deceit, ſelf-ſeeking, reſpecting of Perſons, having mens Perſons in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration for advantage ſake, and ſuch like; for if your eye were ſingle to the Lord alone, ye would deſire no peace at his hands, but in the way of all righteouſneſs fulfilled in your ſelves, yea even to the ſilencing every idle and needleſs word, and the removing of every vain &amp; Aiery thought in you, as knowing that holineſs becomes his houſe for ever; but while ye cannot bear theſe true and faithful ſayings, know ye that ye are alinated in your minds by wicked works which ye are in love with, what ever ye ſhall profeſſe to the contrary, and ſo are alſo out of the faith which gives victory over the world, and all ſin.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:103574:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>And as for your being baptized with water, which is but an outward ſign (at the moſt) of your being dead and buried and riſen with Chriſt, know ye that the thing ſignified muſt be wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed, before the ſign can be truely applyed, which cannot be till ye come to the true faith, and ſo out of the pollutions of the world, for otherwiſe ye ſet a ſeal to a blank, as well as thoſe who ſprinkle infants; neither is Baptiſm with water Chriſts proper Baptiſm, but was begun by <hi>John</hi> who came but to prepare the way of the Lord Chriſt, who was to baptize with the Holy Spirit and fire, who was to increaſe in this his proper work, and <hi>John</hi> to decreaſe in his work; Now I grant that <hi>Johns</hi> Baptiſm was not ſuddenly left off, but decreaſed by degrees as the Saints came to eye and witneſs perfection, ſo as to behold and hold forth Gods purity and righteouſneſs without a ſign; ſo that it was practiced by the Apoſtles and Saints after Chriſts departure, and that ſometimes by way of command, there being (for the preſent) a good uſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hereof, yet <hi>Paul</hi> expreſly declareth (who was a Miniſter to the <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi>) that he was not ſent to baptize but to Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ach glad tid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>gs, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was that Commiſſion of Chriſt to the Apoſtles in <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. a Commiſſion to baptize with water, as I ſhall eviden<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate; for thus are the words truely to be read ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the Greek; <hi>Therefore ys going forth or forward, Diſciple all Nations, dipping or baptizing them into the Name of the Father, Son and Holy Spirit, teaching them to keep all things wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſoever I have commanded you, and behold I am with you al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the dayes, even to the finiſhing of the age;</hi> Hear we ſee, they were to proceed in their work (having firſt waited for power to do it) which was to enter people into the School of Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſt and then to baptize them into the Name of the God-head; Now the Name of the Lord is his ſtrength and power, whereby he is known wonderful in the hearts of his people, ſo, is the Name of the Lord a ſtrong Tower; Now into this name no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could bring them, but the ſame power from on high which the Apoſtles and Saints (that had firſt waited for the ſame in themſelves) received, which power was the Baptiſm of the Spirit, whoſe effect was like unto fire, filling them with a holy jealouſie, and burning up the droſſe, and bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them into unitie with the Father and the Son in the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:103574:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> Spirit, ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> filling their hearts with joy and gladneſs, and put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting words into their mouths, and utterance to declare the wondrous Works of God ſeveral wayes, according to its vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous workings in them, and ſometimes even ſhaking the earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Tabernacle, maki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g them to appear unto the blinde world like drunken men, this Baptiſm which was truely Chriſts own, was (and is altogether neceſſary in the Church of Chriſt, without wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch the work of the Lord in his day could not, nor cannot go on, and therefore was it an Eſſential part of their Commiſſion, which they moſt carefully and faithfully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded; ſo that when Perſons believed (being alſo I deny not then baptized with water) they prayed and laid their hands on them, which was an outward ſign of the bleſſing, and they received the holy Spirit; now if any one ſhall ſay how could the Apoſtles, who were but men, baptize with the Spirit? I anſwer, no otherwiſe then they could at firſt beget faith and repentance in thoſe ſo baptized; it was the Lords work but they miniſterially did it, that is, they having felt the power in themſelves, the raiſed life in them Miniſtred to the life that lay low in others, and ſo brought it up; therefore that the Lord might ſhew he was not tied up to time or manner in the beſtowing of his gift, while <hi>Peter</hi> ſpake thoſe words to <hi>Cornelius</hi> and the reſt, the holy Spirit fell on them that heard the word, ſo that this was the Baptiſm here meant by Chriſt, which was ſo Eſſential to the converſion of the world, and building up of the Saints, in ſo much that <hi>Paul</hi> joyns it with faith as a neceſſary companion, ſaying there is One Lord, one Faith, and one Baptiſme; for by one Spirit are the Saints baptized into one body, Chriſt the baptizer being the head; who moreover told the Apoſtles that he would be with them all the dayes (that is of their Miniſtry) even to the finiſhing of the age; mark, there was an age or certain ſpace of time wherein the truth of the Goſpel ſhould grow, and the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm of the Spirit or the comforters preſence be witneſſed through Chriſts Power accompanying their Miniſtry; and then ſhould the Myſtery of iniquity in falſe Apoſtles get ſuch a head, by ſtealing and bringing in falſe Doctrines, Traditions and inventions, that it ſhould (God ſo permitting it) over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>top the life, and ſo the true Miniſtry ſhould ceaſe, and his living preſence not be felt and enjoyed as before; which
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:103574:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> moſt certainly came to paſſe, as we ſee (whoſe eyes the Lord hath opened) in the many hundred years Apoſtacy and reign of Antichriſt; now if Chriſt meant that <hi>He would be alway with them to the end of the world,</hi> as its falſely rendred in Engliſh Bibles, how could his words be true, ſince we ſee by experience that the Glory of God which ſhined in his Temple in the Apoſtles dayes, departed over the threſhold, the Church went into the wilderneſs, the Seed of God was captivated by the Whore of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and the man-Child (Chriſt in his ſtrength) taken up to God and his Throne; wherefore in the ſecond reſtauration of the ſpiritual Temple and re-edifying of the holy City new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> people muſt firſt come to the true faith, by believing in Chriſt (the true light) and witneſs repentance from all falſe worſhips and and dead works of the world, as thoſe that are wearie of <hi>Babylons</hi> captivity, and that ſet their faces towards <hi>Sion</hi> in truth; and ſo muſt wait with the Lords people in ſilence and humility for the Fathers promiſe, which is the Comforter, even the Spirit of truth, which in his due time baptizeth ſuch with fire, and ſo by degrees leads them into all truth, and out of all ſins and errour, and ſo the Church cometh out of the wilderneſs, leaning upon her beloved, that is, ſtaying her mind upon <hi>the light within,</hi> and being content with her portion, be it much or little, be it judgement or mercy, be it in a day of blackneſs or gloomineſs, or in a day wherein it is neither dark nor light, or in the evening time, wherein it ſhall be light, as ſaith the Prophet, or in the ſun-ſhine of the day it ſelf; ſo not deſpiſing the day of ſmall things, or over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifted up with great things, neither muſt they all this while, ſet upon or practice any outward thing in the worſhip of God, in their own wils, or by imitation of others, or meerly from a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept without, but onely as Chriſt the light ſhall lay that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept upon them; for if they do, they are will-worſhippers, and ſo Idolaters; for as the Son of God was once perſonally preſent in a body of fleſh, commanding the Apoſtles to teach the People (at the firſt raiſing of the Goſpel Church) to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve all things whatſover he had before commanded them, and ſaid unto them, while ſo preſent with them, which the Comforter afterwards brought to their remembrance; ſo in
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:103574:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> the re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>toring thereof the ſecond time, none are to obſerve any thing, or teach any thing to be obſerved, but what Chriſt (manifeſted in their bodies of fleſh) doth command them, for ſaith he, <hi>I go away</hi> (to wit as to his Perſonal body) <hi>and the world ſhall ſee me no more, but ye ſhall ſee me,</hi> that is, in their own bodies manifeſted. Now by this (oh all ye Baptiſts may ye try your ſelves) and preſent practice of water Baptiſm, and all other Adminiſtrations and performances in your Congregations; have ye witneſſed this true faith, or are ye yet diſputing againſt it? have ye repented of all dead works, or are ye ſtill wallowing in the pollutions of the world? have ye waited or do ye wait in ſilence for the Fathers Promiſe, or do ye ſet your ſelves on work in a formal Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and dead praying, and hanging on the lips of ſuch Preachers and Pray-ers? Do ye (or others) keep an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Sabbath (whether on the ſeventh or firſt day) from mens Precepts or a Moſaical Rule, or from a Command of life within? Do ye Baptize and are Baptized, and break Bread from a particular Command in your ſelves, or becauſe the Saints formerly ſo practiſed? Do ye exerciſe the power of the Keyes from the true ſpiritual diſcerning judgement and power, or becauſe the Churches before the Apoſtacy did ſo bind and looſe? Ye muſt know that there hath been a wide ſtep between the Apoſtles and our dayes, and that the gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Church at firſt out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and the bringing it out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> are two ſeveral things, and are not brought to paſs after one and the ſelf-ſame manner, as to the outward adminiſtration of things; Alſo conſider that <hi>Johns</hi> Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was a Propheſie of what things came and muſt come to paſs after the Apoſtles, and not a Relation of what was done in their dayes; ſo that in the coming out of myſtical <hi>Babylon,</hi> the Lambs followers wait on him for the opening of that myſtical Book, as that which concerns their preſent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. Now when the Angel came down from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and lightned the earth with his Glory, whereby the everlaſting Goſpel came to be Preach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, ſaying, <hi>Fear God and give G ory to him, for the hour of his Judgement is come; and come out o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Babylon <hi>my p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ople, and partake not of her ſins leſt ye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of her plagues:</hi> Then as people came out of her by the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:103574:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> guidance of the light, the Temple of God, or his holy Habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation in the Spirit was opened in Heaven; they had a ſight in themſelves into what ſtate they ſhould be brought, even to have a habitation in God, and he in them; but then was this Temple filled with ſmoak from the Glory of God and from his power, that none was able to enter thereinto till the ſeven Plagues of the ſeven Angels were fulfilled; none could fully behold and enjoy the Glory of the Lord till all his Plagues and Judgements were executed upon the Tranſgreſſor and tranſgreſſion within; which being finiſhed, an enterance was miniſtred into the New <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> that came down from God, whoſe light was clear as Chryſtal, and wherein <hi>John</hi> ſaw no Temple, that is, he ſaw no outward Conſtitution of a Church viſible, by thoſe two ſigns of <hi>Water-baptiſm,</hi> and <hi>Laying on of Hands,</hi> which were called the <hi>firſt Beginnings,</hi> or <hi>Principles</hi> in the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> or <hi>breaking of Corporal Bread:</hi> but the Lord God Almighty &amp; the Lamb were the Temple of it; that is, whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver hath a dwelling place in God who is perfectly pure &amp; holy, is (in this day) to be accounted a Member of this holy City, which alſo had no need of the Sun to ſhine by day, nor the Moon by night, nor the light of a Candle, all created helps and ſhadows were uſeleſſe there, for the Lord God alone and the Lamb are the light thereof; ſo that by this Scripture alone are all you <hi>Baptiſts</hi> for ever ſilenced for pleading for a neceſſity of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> or <hi>laying on of Hands,</hi> or <hi>breaking of Bread,</hi> or <hi>Mens Teachings,</hi> or <hi>Scripture-light,</hi> without the <hi>true light</hi> opening them; becauſe after the coming out of <hi>Babylon</hi> there is to be no viſible Temple, ſo as to ſay <hi>lo here, or loe there,</hi> which is by a ſhadow or ſign; nor no need of any ſuch thing to diſtinguiſh the Saints from the World, or lead them up to God, for they ſhall ſee his face even by his immediate light, and his Name ſhall be in their Foreheads, even by his pure Image of Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency and Righteouſneſſe which ſhall moſt plainly appear to the view of the World; and ſo by theſe two things ſhall the Glory of the ſecond Temple be greater than the Glory of the former.</p>
            <p>And if any of you ſhall ſay, <hi>This ſtate and time is not yet come, and therefore the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gns &amp; viſible Adminiſtrations muſt be practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:103574:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>I <hi>Anſwer,</hi> Thoſe that can truly ſay they do believe in Chriſt the Light, and have forſaken ſin as aforeſaid, and are purely moved to be Dipped in Water, &amp;c. to help their weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or in obedience to the inward Command, let them do it and proſper; but let them not ſit down there alwaies, or ſtrive to bring back others thereto that ſee no need thereof, yea rather that it would be but a hurt and cloud unto them; for although many of the Saints (the Lambs followers) yea perhaps moſt do not yet witneſſe a full entrance into the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid Condition, yet in all of them the Temple of God is opened by the light of the Lamb, and the Vials are pouring out daily to deſtroy ſin in them that vails the perfect ſight of God, and ſo now their work is to look ſtedfaſtly forward till all impediments that hinder their perfect and continual Peace be removed, and not to take up their time by the way, about the Exerciſe of thoſe things which muſt not (ſhortly) appear, or be of any uſe: Thus are your skirts alſo diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and your Houſe left unto you deſolate; for ye have not been faithful to that pure Principle of God which (at firſt) ſtirred in ſome of you, and might then move you to be Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized with Water, but are ſet down in a fleſhly reſt, not wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the ſpiritual Baptiſm that ſhould have made you dead to the World, and Crucified you with Chriſt, and alſo have Exerciſed you by its pure Gift in all your worſhippings and goings forth; ſo that ye hereby not growing up in that which is living and eternal, are grown more earthly, ſenſual, dead, carnal and formal than divers years ago when I walked among you; yea even as dead and dry as the Prieſts themſelves, prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching in ſuch a method as they; ſetting up your Desks, and Pulpits, and Clocks, and Hour-glaſſes to ſee how the time goes away, and your Members ſitting (ſome of them) in their Pride, and all of them gazing upon an Image in a Desk or Pulpit; yea, and ſome of you ſo degenerate from your firſt Principles, that ye (as do the <hi>Independants</hi> ſo called) mingle your ſelves with the Nation about ſending out a Miniſtry; yea, and ſome of your Chief Leaders have lately not bluſhed openly to declare, <hi>That you hold it your Duty to ſtand by, and preſerve (ſo much as in you lies) the publick Miniſtry of the Nation,</hi> whom ye judge ought to have their Liberty: So it ſeems ye
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:103574:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> are ready to defend them in offending and afflicting thoſe who in the tenderneſs of their Conſciences, and holy Zeal for the dreadful &amp; pure Name of their God, cannot maintain or feed, but openly oppoſe the falſe Prophets, the Miniſters of Antichriſt, the Emiſſaries of Satan, and deceivers of thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of Souls, of which ſort theſe publick National Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters are, as denying Chriſt Jeſus the Son of God to be both a King, a Prieſt, and a Prophet; which thing you <hi>Baptiſts</hi> ſome years ago did earneſtly affirm and declare; For take away the Law of man from maintaining them to Uſurp upon, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain or Puniſh others, and they are no more than other men: But tis no wonder that ye ſo declare your ſelves, who are ſo far degenerated and leavened with the Principles and Intereſts of theſe <hi>Phariſees</hi> who ſay and do not, that ye ſhew the greateſt Oppoſition to the Saints holy and zealous Practiſes, as irrigular or out of Rule; But ye have not declared what thoſe Practiſes particularly are, nor what rule they are out of, whether that of the Old man, or of the New. Lord, what a Church or Spouſe of Chriſt are theſe pretended Believers Baptized become, who have not a word to plead for him (whom they own to be their Husband) againſt the Beaſt, but would ſubmit in ſilence to any humane Government; nor againſt the falſe Prophet, but have a hand to preſerve him, accounting thoſe that do (in this day of the Lord) oppoſe them both, to be irregular, as though they thereby would caſt the whole bulk of perſecution, and rage, and malice of the multitude upon the Lambs followers, who are called, and choſen, and faithful in their meaſures of life, and as being themſelves afraid what man could and can do unto them: Neither would your <hi>Independant.</hi> Brethren have us to be Countenanced or Intruſted by the Nation, when as none know aright how to Govern others, but thoſe that are themſelves governed by the Lord Jeſus, who are anointed to Govern as well as to Preach, for the ſpirit of true Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is a pure and majeſtical Gift of God, not conſiſting in whoriſh and pompous ſtate, but in the beauty and Glory of ſimple Truth and naked Juſtice, which layes the Rod upon the back of the Tranſgreſſor, and ſmileth upon the wel-doer impartially. And (O Nation) becauſe thou conſidereſt not this, therefore are not thy breaches healed, but rather in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:103574:11"/> unto this day. Oh be ye aſhamed to call your ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>es the Churches of Chriſt, when ye are ſo far out of the Life and Practiſe of the Apoſtles and Prophets, upon whoſe foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the former Churches were builded, Jeſus Chriſt himſelf the true Light being the Head Corner-ſtone; For Conſider whence the word <hi>Church</hi> is derived, even from a word that ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies <hi>to Call out;</hi> ſo that the true Church of Chriſt is a people called out of the Wayes, Wickedneſſes, Formalities, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms and Faſhions of the World, into the pure obedience to, and worſhipping of God in the Spirit by his own living Word which is nigh in the heart and mouth, to which Word ye ſhould do very well to take heed, as to a light ſhining in a dark place, which is your dark hearts, that it may lead you out of all the wayes of ſin, death and deceit into the paths of all Righteouſneſſe, even into ſuch a pure way, wherein no Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venous Beaſt that fights againſt the witneſs of God and his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving truth can ever come ſaith the Lord Almighty, and that becauſe of his flaming Sword which turneth every way, to keep the way of the <hi>Tree of Life</hi> from all ſuch.</p>
            <p>But you will object and ſay, <hi>The Light which thou ſo much ſpeakeſt of and calleſt Chriſt within, as the Enlightner of every man that comes into the World, is no more but a Natural inſtinct or endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or Light of Nature, whereby man is able to reflect upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf when he hath done good or evil, yea and ſometimes reſtrain from the evil, and do the good as well as commit the evil, whereby his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence accuſeth or excuſeth him, for Paul ſaith in his Epiſtle to the Romans, when the Gentiles which have not the Law, do by Nature the things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Law, they having not a Law are a Law unto themſelves; and again the uncircumciſion which is by Nature keeping the Law ſhall judge thee who through the Letter and Circumciſion art a tranſgreſſor of the law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This one thing may for ever ſtop the mouths of all ſuch Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectors, if they would but conſider that (as in the truth it is) <hi>Paul</hi> is not here ſpeaking of any thing, but that which juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies in the ſight of God; for it was not his work to declare to people (being an Apoſtle of Jeſus Chriſt) any Faith, Peace, Reconciliation or Obedience, but what tended to the juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of life; therefore he ſaith before, <hi>that he was not aſhamed of the Goſpel of Chriſt, for it is the Power of God unto Salvation to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one</hi> (Jew <hi>and</hi> Greek) <hi>that believeth;</hi> and therefore he ſaith
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:103574:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> in the thirteenth verſe of the ſecond Chapter, <hi>that the Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Law are not juſt before God, but the doers of the Law ſhall be juſtified;</hi> for when the Gentiles which have not the Law, do by nature the things contained in the Law, theſe having not an outward written Law are a Law to themſelves; whereby they by the Finger of God which wrote the eff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ct of it in their hearts, which is the light of Chriſt that enlightneth every man, are juſtified in the ſight of the living God, or condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his ſight by the ſame Finger or Light, ſo that their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences either excuſed them unto the juſtification and ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their ſouls, or accuſed them unto the damnation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; ſo it is moſt plain, that that Principle whereby they by Nature or Naturally did the will of the Lord, was no other then the light and life of Chriſt, without whom I believe none of you dare deny any one can be juſtified.</p>
            <p>But moreover becauſe of your hardneſſe of belief, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what ye ſay, when ye ſpeak of Nature or doing by Nature; the word Nature comes from a word that ſignifies to be Born; ſo that whatever a man doth by Nature, he doth by that which was born with him or brought forth with him into the World, as beaſts alſo do in their kind, yea and inani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate creatures in their kind; ſo moving and reſt are general works of Nature, becauſe every Creature moveth or reſteth from a Principle which it had from its birth, but here men are apt to commit idolatry in not minding and ſeeing whence this birth or nature, and the works thereof proceeds and do ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, for in the Eternal Power and God-head who was in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf moſt glorious, before any thing was born or brought forth, or before nature was, doth all things, and nature with all its works, ſubſiſt &amp; have their being; ſo that they are nothing but what he is in them, yet every thing in its degree, meaſure and order, and ſo man is in the higheſt degree of acting, from that abilitie which the Creator, who is the Soul of the World and Life of all things placed in him; Now this being rightly conſidered, all that which men in a ſleighting manner are wont to call inſtincts of Nature, or natural light or endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is the very effect of the Life of God himſelf, ſtirring and moving that way; ſo then mankind having an ability in him from his birth to reflect upon himſelf (as to Godward) when he hath done good or evil (which the beaſt is not capable of)
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:103574:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſo as to be accuſed or tormented, or excuſed and comforted, this ability (call it what ye will) is from the life of all things, and the Eternal Word of his Power which is the light and life of men, which cannot be ſeparated from mans underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, whereby the Spirit of a man becomes the Candle of the Lord; and ſo the effect of the Law is written in mans heart by the Finger of God, by Nature, or from his birth, for that word implyeth no more; and in this did the Gentiles differ from the Jews, in that theſe had a law alſo outwardly declared (which was added becauſe of the height of tranſgreſſion againſt the Law in the heart, till the Seed or life that there placed it ſhould ariſe to fulfil it) and the other onely the Principle by Nature or the forced ability from their birth without any out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward engravement or writing, whereupon the Jews boaſted over the Gentiles, becauſe to them were outwardly commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Oracles and Ordinances, &amp;c. Wherefore <hi>Paul</hi> to ſtop their mouths, (for the ſeed was now raiſed) ſaith, <hi>for when the Gentiles which have not a law, do by Nature,</hi> or the Principle pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by God in them from their birth, <hi>the things contained in the law,</hi> theſe having not a Law outwardly written, <hi>are a law to themſelves,</hi> that is, have the Pure Principle of God in themſelves from their birth, ſhewing them what to do, and what to abſtain from, and ſo, if the uncircumciſion which is by Nature keep the Law, that is, if they which are not from their birth cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed outwardly, as not being the Seed of <hi>Abraham</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the fleſh, do keep the Law by the ſame pure Principle of God, they ſhall judge the Jews outward, who having ſuch a a Law and Circumciſion do yet tranſgreſſe the Righteous principle of God, which ſheweth them that inwardly which the law outwardly declareth of, and which Circumciſion out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward holdeth forth; ſo ye may if ye are not wilful, ſee your miſtake in ſeparating Nature from the God of Nature, and that that which naturally ſheweth man what is good and what is evil is the pure principle of God, or the word by which all things were made, which is Chriſt the light; for ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>whatſoever may be known of God is made manifeſt in them,</hi> to wit, by nature or from their birth, for God hath ſhewen it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them which he hath not ſhewen unto a beaſt, becauſe of the lower Region he was created in; ſo that men are not in this
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:103574:12"/> ſence (by nature) Children of Wrath, but Children of the Day, to wit, as man was at firſt brought forth into that which ſhewed him what was good and what was evil, for ſo he was in the Image of God, but as going from the good and chuſing the evil, ſo acting in ſelf in diſtinction from the power or pure Principle of God, which inclination is ſince become natural, or is in him from his birth, and ſo by nature is a Child of Wrath, as the inclination to evil acts it ſelf forth; and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as <hi>Jude</hi> ſpeaketh of ſome, who in whatſoever things they know naturally as living Creatures void of reaſon (for ſo it is in the Greek) in thoſe things they corrupt themſelves, that is not in thoſe things which they know onely from the Eternal light manifeſted in them, which is Gods faithful Witneſſe, which none but a Creature that hath reaſon is capable of, but in things pertaining to the five Senſes of Seeing, Feeling, Taſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Smelling and Hearing; for the Senſitive Beaſt knows by the inſtinct of Nature or from his birth (which is alſo the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of his Creator in him, in his kind) that he is to eat and drink to ſatisfie himſelf, as feeling when he hath enough meat and drink, to give off and chew the cud, or lie down to ſleep, &amp;c. whereas theſe men (as many do now) feaſted and fed without fear inordinately, or drunk inordinately, and ſo cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted themſelves in ſuch things wherein the Beaſt was more moderate; and this is the Natural man that perceiveth not the things of the Spirit of God, the light being obſtructed by ſenſe and ſenſuality in him, and in this ſenſe, whatſoever a man doth by nature, or in his own ſenſual will, diſtinct from the feeling of the Life and Power of God, all that he doth is rejected and accurſed, though the works may be good in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and ſhewen by the Eternal Light; yet he that is chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to the poor, which the light ſheweth to be good, if he give his Alms from a wrong ground or to a wrong end, though he cannot witneſſe acceptation in his Work with the Lord, yet he ſhall judge another who is Rich; and yet ſo cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous that he ſhutteth up his bowels from the Poor and Needy; and ſo might the Gentiles alſo condemn the Jews, though themſelves ſenſually performing ſome good actions were not accepted, becauſe not reconciled to the light in themſelves, which ſhewed the action to be good. But notwithſtanding,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:103574:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> this is a real and infalible Truth, that it is no other than the pure Principle of God, or his Word in the heart which is the true light, that ſheweth man by nature or from his birth, what what is good and evil; which Principle it ſelf was never born or had a beginning, any other-wiſe than was in manifeſtation in man, whoſe Soul came out from the breath of the Almighty (who is out of time) in time.</p>
            <p>But ſome may ſay, <hi>what great hurt or inconvenience can come unto us, though we do not own or believe that which is nigh every man to ſhew him ſin and evil, and which convinceth in his Conſcience to be Chriſt the true light; ſince we believe Chriſt to be the true light in himſelf, and to be tbe Judge, Saviour, Teacher and Comforter of his People, according to the Scriptures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I Anſwer, as <hi>Paul</hi> in another caſe, <hi>much every way;</hi> for firſt, thou ſhalt never come aright to know what is good and what is evil, what is ſin and what is righteouſneſs, but wilt be ready to call good evil, and evil good, and wilt be ſtill in an uncertainty concerning what the good and perfect will of God is, and how then ſhouldeſt thou do it? for thy mind be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing abroad, thou art in the wandring ſtate, and although thou ſearcheſt the Scriptures never ſo narrowly and diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, yet therein will appear thwartings, and contradictions, &amp; ſcruples; not through default of the ſcriptures, but by reaſon that thou art not ſtaid in that which ſhould reconcile them: Hence have aroſe (for many years paſt) thoſe which they call <hi>Caſuites,</hi> who have under-took to Anſwer Caſes of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence for people from the Scriptures; when as thoſe very Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolvers being themſelves from that which ſhould Reſolve all doubts and difficulties, have (like unskil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d Phyſitians) left tender Conſciences half quieted, yea, and oftentimes made the ſcruple and trouble greater than before; and ſo the lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the people have (this way) cauſed them to err. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wilt thou ſo ſee the odiouſneſſe of ſin as it is in it ſelf, and as thou oughteſt to ſee it; for that which ſearcheth and pricketh to the heart, makes men cry out, <hi>What ſhall they do?</hi> they ſeeing ſin ſtaring them in the face with a diſmal Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and how it hath ſeparated them from God the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of all good, they are even at their wits end, and ſo their ſtony and ſtubborn heart comes to be broken, and they are
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:103574:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> willing to deny their wills, luſts and pleaſures for the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his favour whom they have tranſgreſſed againſt; but men may and do hear the plagues and judgements of God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared againſt ſin and ſinners in the Scriptures a long time, as God ſhall wound the hairie ſcalp of him that goes on in his wickedneſs, the wicked ſhall be turned into hell, and all that forget God, how that their worm ſhall never die nor fire never be quenched, that they ſhall have their part in the lake which burns with fire and brimſtone which is the ſecond death, and ſuch like, and yet they never be moved at it, but either are apt not to believe it, or to put the day of evil far from them; for all outward Declarations or threatnings without that which rips man open, and ſet him naked and bare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord, are but as ſhot that flies over the head, but never toucheth the body, and ſo do no execution upon the tranſgreſſour. So neither can man, if at any time he be woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for ſin, be truely healed and comforted, becauſe that which ſmites muſt heal, and that onely: Now if any one ſee his ſickneſs as <hi>Ephraim</hi> did, and go not to the true Phyſitian, but go to <hi>Egypt,</hi> how ſhould he have a true and thorow cure? Now at ſuch a time, one may fetch and gather in all the promiſes in the Scriptures and endeavour to apply them or have them applied to himſelf, and ſtrive to believe that they do belong to him, and yet be never a jot the nearer to Peace with the living God; and how many have deceived themſelves this way, and like children quieted themſelves a while, but afterwards conſcience and they have more fallen at odds then before; for the ſoul being inviſible and immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, an outward Declaration or promiſe cannot ſatisfie it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that is received in by the ſences of ſeeing or hearing, the ſound and ſight whereof vaniſheth; but the voice of the Lord in the inviſible and immortal and Eternal light and love, makes up all breaches in the ſoul be they never ſo wide, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying unto the wounded conſcience the blood of ſprinkling, and waſhing and cleanſing, and ſo ſpeaks in Truth and reali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty better things then that of <hi>Abel.</hi> Neither after the work of regeneration begun and in meaſurewitneſſed, can any one that believes not in nor ſtayeth his mind on the inviſible immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal light within him, be preſerved againſt the ſnares and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilties
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:103574:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> that do attend him, and the many Temptations, and ſundry tryals, that do befall him, whereby he ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to the end and be ſaved, for the Light is his Armour, the Word nigh in his heart and mouth is his ſword, which are to be with him continually; the light is the leaven of the Kingdom, that works into and preſerves in the ſavoury Life, it is the immortal hand that keeps the Soul faſt to it ſelf that it maketh not ſhip-wrack of Faith and a good Conſcience: and though there may be never ſo many opinions in the World taken up and contended for, with or about the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, or never ſo many <hi>Atheiſtical</hi> opinions contradicting the Scriptures, yet the immortal Eternal light reſiding and and ſhining in the heart, being believed and waited in, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes the Anchor of the Soul ſure and ſtedfaſt, reconciles the Scriptures, and makes the Soul to triumph over all Rant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and <hi>Atheiſtical</hi> ſpirits, to rejoyce in the hope of the glory of God, and to ſtrive againſt every thing that may Eclips it; So ſhut not your eye oh ye Profeſſors, neither cavil againſt the Univerſal, ſaving, neceſſary light of the Lamb, for though Chriſt Jeſus be light and Life in himſelf, yet that can avail you nothing unleſs he be ſo in you; till which time, all the light and knowledge that is in you from without, is darkneſs, and then, how great is it?</p>
            <p>And now (Oh ye <hi>Fift Monarchy-men,</hi> as ye are called) muſt you be ſearched and tryed by the Ballance of the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary, to ſee whether your ſword of ſteel be the right wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon which the man of God muſt uſe to prepare and make way for Chriſts Kingdom in the world; that ye are very great oppoſers of the true light within I know, and muſt needs be, while ye are in this Principle; that there were four eminent worldly <hi>Monarchies</hi> or Kingdoms (to wit) the <hi>Aſſyrian, Perſian, Macellonian,</hi> and <hi>Romane,</hi> I grant, who had their time to riſe and fall, ſo that the Tyrany of the laſt of theſe, which is the worſt of theſe, is drawing nigh to its period; and that in the dayes of theſe Kings, the God of Heaven hath and will ſet up a Kingdom that ſhall never be deſtroyed, as ſaith the Prophet <hi>Daniel,</hi> I know and ſee; but that this Kingdom ſhall be Uſhered in, by ſuch groſſe outward obſervation, and Busſle, as ye imagine, or that it ſhall be adminiſtred when ſet
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:103574:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> up, in ſuch a way and manner as ye think, I utterly deny; for if ye will come to the Scriptures, which ye ſeem much to adhere to (though in a very literal ſence) let us ſee what they teſtifie both of the way of ſetting it up, the nature of the King or <hi>Monarch</hi> that ruleth, and the manner of his Government; when Chriſt the Son of God, the firſt born among many bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, was bringing into the World, before the Tyrany of Antichriſt got up, this very Kingdom was approaching, and there was a meſſenger ſent to prepare his way, even <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt, who was a plain man, of plain raiment, and mean fare, crying in the wilderneſs, prepare ye the way of the Lord, make his pathes ſtraight, which was to be done by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance from ſin; for ſaith he, <hi>Repent for the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is at hand;</hi> Now at that very time was the <hi>Romane</hi> Empire or <hi>Monarchy</hi> at a great height, and Tyranized over the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued <hi>Jews,</hi> and was groſly and heatheniſhly Idolatrous, and the blind <hi>Jews</hi> thought Chriſt their King, when he came would have redeemed them out of that thraldom by ſome external power, ſo reſtoring (as they imagined) the Kingdom to <hi>Iſrael;</hi> but alas they were much deceived in thoſe their expectations; for his Kingdom was of another nature, ſo that <hi>John</hi> his fore-runner, came onely Preaching Repentance, and bearing witneſs to him as the true light (that lightneth every man) to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved in, which ſhould lead thereunto, neither did Chriſt himſelf while on the Earth, or any of his Diſciples in that time, uſe any other means, or Preach any other Doctrine in order to this Kingdom, which before ſome of them ſhould taſte of death, he teſtified they ſhould ſee it come in power; neither hath Chriſt two Kingdoms, the one ſpiritual, and the other Perſonal, as ye diſtinguiſh, for in his Perſonal ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance he ſuffered and was deſpiſed, but in his ſpiritual ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance he rejoyceth and triumpheth World without end. Nor was the Reign of Antichriſt the ruine and deſtruction of that his Kingdom which was ſet up in the Apoſtles dayes (for he ſtill made good his Title in the hearts of ſome, one way or other, in the darkeſt times, as he that had right to Reign) but onely was withdrawn a while that he might the ſecond time come upon the necks of his enemies with the greater force, but it muſt ſtill be in the ſame ſpiritual way, for the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:103574:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> is but one now as before; wherefore doth he now prepare his way as in times paſt, by calling upon all men to repent &amp; forſake the evil of their ways, by believing in his light within them, which diſcovers it unto them, that they may feel his living power; and ſo ſaith <hi>John</hi> in his Revelation, <hi>That the Lamb makes War with the Beaſt by the ſword which proceedeth out of his mouth, and with the breath of his lips muſt he ſlay the wicked,</hi> ſo that all ye who treaſure up carnal weapons, which ye ſay, are to be reſerved againſt a day of ſlaughter, when ye ſhall by the Lord (as ye ſuppoſe) be bid to ſtrike, are no fit inſtruments in Gods hand, or in his work, yea ye have no part nor lot in this matter, but are carryed on with a <hi>Jehu's</hi> zeal, breathing out threatnings, which (if ye ſtop not your furious courſe) will end in your deſtruction; for he that ſmites with the ſword ſhall periſh by it. Conſider alſo what a King or <hi>Monarch</hi> this is (who is to Reign in righteouſneſs over all) that ye ſeem to be ſo zealous for; I give my Teſtimony with <hi>Paul</hi> (as I have felt him in my meaſure) thus concerning him; <hi>I charge thee,</hi> ſaith he to <hi>Timothy, in the ſight of God who quickeneth all things, and before Chriſt Jeſus, who before Pontius Pilate wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed a good confeſſion, that thou keep this Commandment (which was to fight the good fight of Faith and follow after righteouſneſs, godlineſs, patience, meekneſs, love,</hi> &amp;c.) without ſpot unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bukeable, till the appearing of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; which in his times he ſhall ſhew, who is the bleſſed and onely Potentate, the King of Kings and Lord of Lords; who onely hath im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie, dwelling in the light which no man can ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach unto (to wit in his own wiſdom) or with his bodily eye, whom no man hath ſeen, nor can ſee (to wit with thoſe) to whom be honour and Power everlaſting, <hi>Amen.</hi> Oh that ye ſword-men had your eyes opened to behold this King as he is here witneſſed, how would you then be aſhamed, and amazed at your own folly in gazing upwards, as expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſee him in a bodily ſhape and with a corporal eye, to Reign on Earth; Here you ſee <hi>Paul</hi> witneſſeth he ſhall be ſhewn in his times, and that as the onely Potentate or <hi>Monarch,</hi> and yet he ſaith no man can ſee him; what a contradiction may this ſeem to be to your groſſe underſtandings; but it is really ſo, I averre; for his appearance in the world in his
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:103574:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> times, muſt be agreeable to his nature; he onely hath immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, therefore muſt be ſeen onely by that which is immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, he dwelleth in the light, and therefore muſt be beheld onely in the light, and by an eye internally enlightned; So that now ſtop your mouths for ever, and ceaſe from your carnal interpretations of thoſe Scriptures which ſpeaks of Chriſts coming to reign on earth; but turn to within, even to his light wherewith every one of you are enlightned, that in that light ye may ſee him who is inviſible, dwelling in the light, whom no man hath nor can ſee nor ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach unto; for aſſure your ſelves that the world ſhall ſee his bodily Shape and Perſon no more; but the Saints do and ſhall ſee him, for becauſe he liveth they ſhall live alſo. And as for the manner of this ſpiritual Kings Government, it muſt be ſpiritually, not by an outward viſible ſhining body, quel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and over-awing the enemies of his Kindomg, but by his inward and inviſible Power in the hearts of his People, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the people to fall under him, or chaining them up; yea, making all his enemies within and without to go backward and flee before him; and although ye may look upon this as a weak &amp; inconſiderable thing, becauſe it ſeems not pompous to your carnal eye, yet know that it is of the greateſt force that can be imagined; For is not Conſcience more to a man than a thouſand witneſſes? Which if it once condemn, God is greater and knoweth all things, and ſo the comment of the wicked increaſeth; Now that of Chriſt in the Saints ariſing in Power, and transforming them into its own Image of Righteouſneſs and true Holineſs, his Name is ſeen in their foreheads by living fruits, which reaching to the witneſs of God in wicked men, they cannot ſtand before it; for the wicked cannot ſtand in Judgement, nor ſinners in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of the Righteous, becauſe by the Righteous Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of God in themſelves they are Judged, which worketh in their guilty Conſciences the fear and flaſhes of Eternal ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, which fierce indignation of the Almighty, that they may avoid, they alſo are oft times brought to lay hold of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Life, bringing forth fruits meet for Repentance; and ſo the work of the Lord proſpereth in this his King immortal, his hand, in his Majeſty riding proſperouſly, becauſe of Truth
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:103574:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> and Meekneſs and Righteouſneſs, and his right hand teaching him terrible things, and brings to paſs greater things hereby than all outward force, fear and violence were able to do. Now the reaſon why ye ſavour not ſuch things as theſe, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ye (with many other Profeſſours) are out from that which ſhould give you ſalt in your ſelves to ſavour withal, and ſo being buried in the Letter of the Scriptures, do interpret them according to a mind that is under the miniſtration of the Letter, and not of the Spirit; So look what truths of God are to be ſpiritually underſtood and diſcerned, ye being out of the light, do literally underſtand, and ſo are for an exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal or perſonal appearance of Chriſt in his Kingdom, even as a fifth viſible Monarch in the world, and for a Holy City out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, juſt ſo long and broad, and every way compoſed, as that deſcription of it in the <hi>Revelation</hi> ſeemeth outwardly to deſcribe; So ye will talk, and be even very zealous for a New Heaven and a New Earth wherein dwelleth Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but what fruit doth the expectation of ſuch things (in your way expected) bring forth in you? Doth it make you diligent to be found of him in Peace, without ſpot and blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, as <hi>Peter</hi> exhorted the Saints to be, who looked for ſuch things? Or are you in the vanities and folly of the multitude, who are without Hope or God in the world? How proud, rough, rugged, earthly-minded, bitter, dead, dry and unſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voury do many of you appear? Oh People, it is not a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of, or expectation of great and outward changes or happineſs, though for ever to endure, that will bring to the Croſs of Chriſt, and ſlay the enmity of your minds by wicked works, but it is the knowing the Croſs of Chriſt in your ſelves, which is his living and quickning Power, felt by wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his light, that muſt bring you to take up your own croſs and follow him: elſe while you think to be the men that ſhall Reign with Chriſt and Judge the world, ye your ſelves will be Judged by Chriſt in this his day, which cometh and is come as a ſnare upon all the earth. Your good inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions towards the executing of Juſtice and Righteouſneſs in the earth, in oppoſition to Tyranny and Oppreſſion, I confeſs is to be owned, but ye take not the right courſe how to bring it forth; for it is not the ſhaking a Weapon, or ſore threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:103574:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> or the like, at the Beaſt that will change his nature, but it is the Life that is the light of men which will do it, for that which alone ſearcheth the heart, can and doth alone turn the ſame, ſo that if (as the Lambs true followers) ye knew how to make War in Righteouſneſs with the Whore, Beaſt &amp; falſe Prophet, through Faith &amp; Patience ye might &amp; ſhould do good; but if out of a raſh and blind zeal ye will ſteer an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>direct courſe, no wonder if you arrive not at your deſired Harbour; for if ye will needs give blows, ye muſt expect blows again, becauſe this exaſperates the proud and wilful na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, whoſe Element it is even to live in the fire: alſo an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward force to an outward, is like to like; but a ſpiritual Power againſt a carnal is altogether different, and what ſhall alway ſtand againſt Gods living Power in Spirit, by whom all things were made, and in which they all ſubſiſt, and by which all hearts are bridled? <hi>Saul</hi> was a ſtout and valiant Warriour, and higher than the reſt by the head and ſhoulders, and went in and out a notable Chieftain before the People; but when Gods witneſs accuſed him, he was as weak as water, yea, fell down upon his face to the ground; So now we keeping cloſe to this, as the Head-ſtone in the Corner, the Weapon we War withal, though it be managed with much Meekneſs and Patience (as it ought to be) is far ſtronger than yours that keeps a greater clattering, for yours hath yet wrought no deliverance in the earth, nor never will; but thouſands (Glory be to the Lord God of Power) can witneſs deliverance from the unjuſt power, and from Injuſtice and unrighteouſneſs in thought, word and deed, even by the Armour of light, which is Gods faithful witneſs within them, and the Government placed upon his ſhoulders, who by his moſt powerful and good Spirit will in due time Govern the Nations Righteouſly upon the earth, and in no other way; Therefore I adviſe you to put up your Sword of Steel into his Sheath for ever, yea, to break him into a Plow-ſhare; for ſo he may be of ſome good uſe among mankind; and wreſtle not ſo againſt fleſh and blood, as to kill the Creature; which is Gods Workmanſhip, but come to know the Weapons of the Saints Warfare, which are not carnal but ſpiritual, yet migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty through God to the pulling down all the Strong-holds of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:103574:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſin and ſinners both within and without; for ſaith <hi>Paul, They have in readineſs to revenge every diſobedience, when your obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</hi> (ſpeaking to the Saints) <hi>is fulfilled;</hi> So then, if ye will be accounted of the number of the Saints that follow the Lamb in his Holy War, wait to feel his living Power in your own Particulars, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> may fulfil your obedience towards him: and then ſhall the ſame Power (appearing in you) be able to revenge all diſobedience in others, be they Magiſtrates, Prieſts or People; but if ye live in the diſobedience your ſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Gods faithful witneſs, which is his true light within you, and come not to the Croſs of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, which maketh Humble and Meek, ſlayeth the earthly mind, and brings out of ſelf and all ſelfiſh wayes into the true ſelf-denial, which is to Love and give Glory onely to God, and to love ones Neighbour as ones ſelf (which to do aright (the light waited in in truth) will diſcover) your out-cries againſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wickedneſs and injuſtice will be but as the eſpial of a Mote in anothers eye, when as a Beam is ſtill in your own.</p>
            <p>But ye will ſay, That Chriſt Luke 22.36. a little before his ſuffering, bad the Diſciples, <hi>That he who had not a Sword ſhould ſell his Garment and buy one:</hi> which could not be but for ſome great and neceſſary uſe, that the having of it ſhould be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before a neceſſary Garment.</p>
            <p>Can ye ſay in truth of heart, and nothing within you tell you that ye lye, that what Chriſt (in this Particular) ſaid to the eleven, that he in them ſpake to all Saints who ſhould come after? As he did when he exhorted them to Watch, ſaying, <hi>What I ſay unto you, I ſay unto all, Watch;</hi> Or was this Sword that he bid them to buy onely for ſome ſpecial uſe at the time of his apprehenſion? Which was to hold forth, that all ſuch fighting with the Sword by the Saints was now to take its farewel in the world: Chriſt was made under the Law, which both tolerated, and oft times commanded the Jews not onely to defend themſelves, but to offend their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; ſo an eye for an eye, a tooth for a tooth; and he was not yet offered up which put an end to the Law: alſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve his reaſon for his ſo ſpeaking; for (ſaith he) <hi>I ſay unto you, that this which is written muſt be accompliſhed in me;</hi> And he
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:103574:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> was reckoned among the tranſgreſſours: for the things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning me have an end; intimating hereby that the buying of the Sword was for the very forementioned purpoſe, and when the things written concerning his ſufferings were finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, then the outward Sword muſt be put up and laid aſide, as he bid <hi>Peter</hi> to do, when he had once ſmitten with it, leaſt he periſhed by it. Likewiſe mark his anſwer to them, when they ſaid there were two Swords: ſaith he, <hi>It is enough;</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he ſeemed to ſay before, that every one ſhould ſell his Garment (that had not a Sword) to buy one: ſhewing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, that this thing was not of Univerſal uſe, as ye would un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand: therefore when <hi>Judas</hi> had betrayed him to the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and thoſe about him ſaid unto him, <hi>Lord ſhall we ſmite with the ſword?</hi> And one of them had ſmitten and cut off the High Prieſts ſervants ear; Chriſt anſwered and ſaid, <hi>Suffer ye thus far?</hi> Shewing, that now the Sword had done his Office: <hi>And ſo he touched his ear &amp; healed him;</hi> Thus exerciſing his Power of love in requiting good for evil, and even making up the breach that the Sword had made in revenge: neither was any ſign of a Sword ſeen in the hands of any of the Apoſtles and Saints after Chriſts departure, but they ſuffered with all Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience through faith in the Power of God, &amp; ſo muſt &amp; do the Lambs true followers in this his day of reſtoring the deſolate Places, as <hi>John</hi> teſtifies in his Book of <hi>Revelation;</hi> he that killeth with the Sword, muſt be killed by the Sword; here is the Patience and Faith of the Saints. And as for divers Scriptures that ſpeak of the Lords overturning again &amp; again, till he come to Reign whoſe Right it is, and of puniſhing the ſtout heart of the Oppreſſour, and of waſting utterly thoſe Nations that will not ſerve the Church, and ſuch like: they muſt be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of the exerciſing of Chriſts Power in Peoples hearts, and alſo of juſtly ſuffering the falſe and unrighteous powers of the earth to ſcourge and deſtroy each other for their ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, till they come to ſerve and fear the Lord in Truth, which brings into Peace and Unity, for the Devils kingdom is divided againſt it ſelf, but <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is a City in Unity with it ſelf; but that the Saints ſhall and ought to have a hand in theſe outward deſolations, as moved thereto by the Spirit of the Lord, I deny; for, his Kingdom in them ſtands in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, peace and joy in the Holy Spirit, which they are
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:103574:18"/> to hold forth viſibly before all men, and not their hands to act contrary to their hearts.</p>
            <p>Now come we to you called <hi>Seekers,</hi> to try what ye ſeek after, ſtick at, and whether ye ſeek the Lord in a right way: that it is a pretious thing to ſeek the Lord and his Way of Righteouſneſs in truth, all the Righteous and upright in heart do experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally know; for ſeek and ye ſhall find ſaith Chriſt (the true light) to his; and bleſſed are they that keep his Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, and ſeek him with the whole heart; and ſaith <hi>David</hi> in another place, <hi>Let all thoſe that ſeek thee, rejoyce and be glad in thee;</hi> and it is Propheſied by the Prophet <hi>Jeremy,</hi> that when the Jews had been in the captivity of <hi>Babylon,</hi> they ſhould go and ſeek the Lord their God, asking their way to <hi>Sion</hi> (from which they had been captivated) with their faces thitherward, ſaying, <hi>Come and let us joyn our ſelves to the Lord in a perpetual Covenant that ſhall not be forgotten;</hi> Mark, when they were weary of their captivity, they ſhould go and ſeek, not ſtand ſtill and enquire onely, but aske with their faces thitherward, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Come let us joyn to the Lord, &amp;c.</hi> actually to ſet about the work; Therefore ſaith the Lord by the Prophet, in the 8th verſ. of the 50th Chapter, <hi>Remove out of the midſt of</hi> Babylon, <hi>and go forth out of the Land of the</hi> Chaldeans, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which the Prophet <hi>Zachary</hi> alſo ſecondeth, ſaying, <hi>Deliver thy ſelf oh</hi> Sion <hi>that dwelleth with the Daughter of</hi> Babylon; So, here is a lively re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation of the Lords bringing his ſpiritual Seed out of ſpiritual captivity, after the long night of Apoſtacy; <hi>Babylon</hi> or <hi>Confuſion</hi> was the ſtate they were to depart from, <hi>Sion</hi> or the Mountain of Holineſs was the State they were to come to, and in order hereunto, they were to move and ſet forward, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was there any ſtation by the way where they were to ſet down or continue. This I ſpeak for your ſakes who for divers years have ſeemed to turn your backs upon the Whore of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> as ſeeing and diſliking the falſe doctrines, wayes and worſhips of Antichriſt, whereby you have been deceived and captivated; but (as though the Paſſage to <hi>Sion</hi> or <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was ſtopped up) ye have ſit down by the way, ſaying, The Church is yet in the Wilderneſs, where ſhe muſt abide, till God makes way for her coming forth, which is by raiſing up his witneſſes, who muſt appear with Miracles and ſuch ſigns as the Apoſtles did to confirm their Miniſtry by, till which time
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:103574:18"/> there is no true Goſpel Miniſtry, nor Adminiſtration of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, or any Ordinances of a viſible Church. This ſeems in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed to carry a face of truth with it, and hath ſtumbled ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; but conſider firſt, whether ye are not ſome of thoſe falſe prophets which Chriſt ſaid ſhould come and ſay, <hi>Lo here, and lo there:</hi> whether ye are not thoſe that ſay, Chriſt is in the Deſart, as yet retired as to his viſible appearance in the world, whom to go forth after, the Saints muſt not, but muſt keep their own Habitations in the light, to which they have been turned; for ſaith he, <hi>As the lightning riſeth in the Eaſt and ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth even unto the Weſt, ſo ſhall the coming of the Son of man be;</hi> and <hi>Luke</hi> addeth, <hi>in his day;</hi> So then here is a plain token of the Day of the Son of man, or the ſign of the Son of man in Heaven (to wit, in the true Church viſible, at his coming) when he cometh as a Univerſal light that hath enlightned eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man that cometh into the world, by whoſe guidance and direction (they believing in it) all may come out of the falſe wayes and worſhips and deceits of the Whore of <hi>Babylon,</hi> or of the whole world, and out of all ſin into the way of Truth, Purity, Peace and true Worſhip, to ſerve the Lord in Spirit and Truth with one conſent: and thoſe (who have believed in this true light themſelves) which makes manifeſt all ſin and deceit, and having waited therein, have felt it to be the light of life unto them, quickning their Souls up to God, and Baptizing them with its Holy Fire, ſo making his living Word to be as fire in their bones, and putting words into their mouths to teſtifie and declare againſt the Beaſt and falſe prophet, and againſt the world that their deeds are evil, and to call them to Repentance, by believing in the ſame light in themſelves, which is Chriſt the true Prophet, Gods faithful witneſs, and are true and living witneſſes for his Name, and ſuch as preach the Everlaſting Goſpel or glad Tidings, although they ſpeak in no Language but their Mother Tongue, do no outward Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, as to heal the ſick, cleanſe the Lepers or the like; nor do at all practiſe Baptizing with water, laying on of hands, or breaking of bread; And thus I plainly demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate it to any that are not wilfully blind. The Jewiſh ſtate of old was the true figure of the Goſpel Church, after the Son of God his being manifeſted in the fleſh, who was the end of all figures and ſhadows: look then in what manner the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:103574:19"/> Lord brought forth and led the Jew outward then, ſo doth he bring forth and lead the Jew inward afterwards; Now when the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> came firſt out of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> they were brought out of that houſe of bondage with a high hand and ſtretched-out arm, as to the outward: <hi>Moſes</hi> was loath to go, as thinking they would not believe him, therefore the Lord gave him a ſigne of turning the Rod into a Serpent; which he did alſo before hard-hearted <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> upon whom were ten viſible Plagues alſo ſent; the Sea was divided, the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> drowned, the Rock guſhed out water, <hi>Jericho</hi> fell by the blowing of Rams Horns, and the like: in this high manner came they to <hi>Canaan;</hi> but when they for their iniquity, were led into captivity by the King of <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> at their coming out the ſecond time, there was no ſuch outward ſign ſhewen, or any ſuch viſible work wrought in order to their deliverance; but (as thoſe who had a right to a reſtauration of that which once they gained by ſuch hardſhips and mighty works) this was Gods way of proceeding towards them; he raiſed up <hi>Cyrus</hi> to make a Proclamation of liberty, and to reſtore the treaſure and veſſels of the Temple, which was a lively figure of Chriſt the ſpiritual King, Proclaming in the hearts of his People by the true light, which is his word, that they ſhould now leave all falſe, and wicked, and deceitful wayes of the Whore of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and bring back the veſſels of the ſpiritual Temple to ſerve and worſhip God in his holy mountain <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that they be no longer defiled and profaned by Idol wayes and worſhips; then, upon this Proclamation of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> thoſe whoſe hearts were touched, and whoſe ſpirits were ſtirred up, as <hi>Zerubbabel, Joſhuah</hi> and others, ſtood not ſtill, but ſet about the work, leading many <hi>Jewes</hi> to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> without any more ado (as <hi>Nehemiah</hi> did alſo afterwards by the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of <hi>Artaxerxes</hi>) and when they came thither they went to build the Temple, although the enemies made them ceaſe a while by force, then the Prophets <hi>Haggai</hi> and <hi>Zechariah</hi> propheſied (but did no miracle) unto the <hi>Jews that were in Judah and Jeruſalem, in the Name of the Lord God of Iſrael,</hi> Ezra 5. verſ. 1. <hi>whereupon Zerubbabel,</hi> and <hi>Joſhua</hi> aroſe up and began to build the houſe of God, for it is ſaid Hag. 1. the Lord ſtirred
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:103574:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> up their ſpirits ſo to do, and the ſpirits of all the remnant of the People, for they were in the unbelief before (as ye are) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the time, ſaying <hi>Hag.</hi> 2. <hi>ver.</hi> 2. the time is not come, the time that the Lords houſe ſhould be built, then the Lords Word in <hi>Haggai</hi> was this, to convince them of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; Is it time for you, oh ye, to dwell in your ſieled houſes, and this houſe lay waſt; now therefore thus ſaith the Lord, conſider your wayes, &amp;c. And afterwards when the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Temple was built, they were apt to have low thoughts of it; who is left among you ſaith the ſame Prophet, that ſaw this houſe in the firſt glory, and how do ye ſee it now? is it not in your eyes in compariſon of it as nothing (mark) as nothing, yet ſaith he now be ſtrong, oh <hi>Zerubbabel,</hi> ſaith the Lord, and be ſtrong oh <hi>Joſhuah</hi> the high Prieſt, and be ſtrong all ye people of the Land ſaith the Lord, and work; for I am with you ſaith the Lord of hoſts, according to the word that I covenanted with you, when ye came out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> ſo my ſpirit remaineth among you, fear ye not; for thus ſaith the Lord of hoſts, yet once it is a little while, and I will ſhake the Heavens and the Earth and the Sea, and the dry Land; and I will ſhake all Nations, and the deſire of all Nations ſhall come, and I will fill this houſe with Glory ſaith the Lord of hoſts; the ſilver is mine and the gold is mine ſaith the Lord of hoſts; the Glory of this latter houſe ſhall be greater then of the former, ſaith the Lord of hoſts, and I will give peace in this place ſaith the Lord of hoſts; are not theſe plain words to him that deſires to underſtand, the people were diſcouraged, becauſe their ſecond Temple was not ſo Stately and pompous outwardly as the firſt built by <hi>Solomon;</hi> yet were they bid to be ſtrong or of a good courage, for the Lord of hoſts (ſtrong and mighty) was with them, and the ſame ſpirit remained among them, according to his Covenant with them when they came out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> though there were not miracles and ſuch viſible ſignes ſhewed amongſt them now, as then (for the right of building the ſecond Temple ſtood in the Covenant, which was ſtill the ſame to the Seed of <hi>Iſrael</hi> outward, he to be their God and they to be to him a People, whereof Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion in the fleſh was a ſign, as the Circumciſion of the heart is a ſigne of the ſpiritual and everlaſting Covenant to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:103574:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> the ſpiritual Seed) ſaying they ſhould not fear, for he would ſhortly ſhake all, and all Nations by his powerful witneſs, which ſhould make way for Chriſt to come and fill his ſecond houſe with his Glory, (for all ſpiritual riches and treaſures are His and in Him) ſo that the Glory of the latter houſe ſhould be greater then of the former, to wit, in the inviſible Glory (yet viſible by fruits of all righteouſneſs) which to bring forth, was the ſum and end of all figures, ſhadowes, miracles, tongues and propheſies; So that they ſhould have peace in God which paſſeth all Humane underſtanding and outward reſt alſo when their ſufferings were fulfilled. Now conſider whether it were not juſt ſo, in the firſt raiſing up of the Goſpel Church in the Apoſtles dayes, they had the gift of tongues, they did many miracles, &amp;c. for it was meet and needful at the firſt bringing in of the firſt born into an unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving and Heatheniſh world, that it ſhould be ſo, as it was at the <hi>Jews</hi> coming out of <hi>Egypt</hi> to be a viſible Nation and People unto God; but at the coming out of myſtical <hi>Babylon</hi> the Spirit of Life from God entred ſaith <hi>John</hi> into the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, and they ſtood upon their feet, and they propheſied, no miracle, or in what Language it was, being mentioned, and the way that the Saints overcame was by the blood of the Covenant; mark, the ſame Life of Chriſt which is the blood of the everlaſting Covenant which the Apoſtles and Saints formerly ſtood in was in them, whereby they got victory every way; alſo they overcame by the Word of their Teſtimony, declaring what they had ſeen and handled of the Word of Life, and by ſuffering for the ſame, even unto death, as the <hi>Jew</hi> outward adventured their lives in the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on with their work, againſt <hi>Sanballat, Tobiah</hi> and the other their cruel enemies; neither is this ſecond work of God to be ſleighted, or little eſteemed; for it is done by the pure power of the Almighty in the Spirit, as the Prophet <hi>Zacharie</hi> teſtified ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, not by might nor by power, that is, ſo viſibly appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in ſtrange gifts, but by my Spirit ſaith the Lord of hoſts, even that by whom all things were made, and ſo is very great, and ſhall bring forth the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reſt State of the Church that ever was, as in the deſcription of the new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the Holy City, doth moſt evidently appear; <hi>wherein ſhall be a new Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and new Earth, wherein dwelleth righteouſneſs,</hi> which <hi>Peter</hi> and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:103574:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> the Saints in his dayes waited for and deſired to ſee; where ſhall be no more ſorrow, nor crying, nor pain, nor night; and this is the State after the captivity, not wrought out by outward ſignes and wonders, but by the Internal light lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of all that is unclean, into that wherein there is no defilement, which is a glorious and all powerful work, ſo that the Saints feeling of it, ſhall, yea and do already ſay, now is come Salvation and ſtrength, and the Kingdom of our God and the Power of his Chriſt, for the accuſer of our brethren is caſt down, which accuſed them before our God day and night; and this purely ſpiritual way of proceeding, is moſt ſuitable to deſtroy the myſtery of iniquity, for here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſpiritual Wiſdom is ſet in oppoſition, and doth diſcover ſpiritual deceit, by which the Nations have been made drunk; yet we deny not, or limit the Power of the Holy One in this his day, to come forth in what gifts he pleaſeth, as ſometimes he hath done by healing and extraordinary faſtings amongſt us; but this we ſay, it is not ſo much a ſeal to the Miniſtry, as the Lords free working how he pleaſeth; and how he will pleaſe to come forth hereafter, when the Truth ſhall actual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prevail over other Nations that do not profeſſe Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, we are not much careful, as knowing that whatſoever is needful for the managing of the Lords own Work, himſelf will freely beſtow, whether it be the gift of tongues, miracles or any other. Neither is it neceſſary that the true Miniſtry ſhould be the Adminiſtratours of baptiſm with water, laying on of hands, or breaking of bread, at their riſing, ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituting a Church (called viſible) by thoſe outward ſigns and ſhadows, nay it is not convenient that they ſhould do ſo for the reaſons forementioned to the Baptiſts; alſo, for as much as Antichriſt under pretence of ſetting up of outward falſe Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrations, called by him Ordinances, and crying them up, hath betrayed the pure life in Spirit; and ſeeing others alſo (as the Baptiſts themſelves) who have profeſſed to Miniſter thoſe Ordinances in a right manner and to true Subjects thereof, have idolized the ſame, and become dead, dry and barren therein, miniſtring out of the life and Power, and in a formality; therefore the Lord, as he hath done (in ſuch caſes) leaveth them to ſuch Traytors, Idolaters and formaliſts,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:103574:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> as going out of them, and leading his People (in this his day) in a different manner, even in a pure path of righteouſneſs in the Spirit manifeſted by its own immediate fruits; and bringing them into that wherein they ſee no Temple (beſides the Lord God and the Lamb) to dwell in, ſo that ye called Seekers, waiting (as ye ſay) for a right Adminiſtrator of Baptiſme, &amp;c. do but from the deſart look for the Kingdom to come with an outward obſervation, when as the Kingdom of God is within you, as it was in the Phariſees, if ye could ſo ſee it; for the light is that in which God dwelleth, and by which he dwelleth in man either as a reprover and condemner, or juſtifier and comforter, and that by which he Reigneth in him as a Judge or Saviour, which is Chriſt his Son given by him for a Covenant of light to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> which Covenant any one taking hold of, is brought into it, and ſo hath a right to come out of <hi>Babylon</hi> to <hi>Sion,</hi> yea, muſt come out thence leaſt he be found a tranſgreſſour againſt it, for that which ſheweth him where he hath been and whither he is to go, will give him ſtrength, he waiting therein, to paſſe on, till he come to appear before God in <hi>Sion</hi> which is the beautie of Holineſs.</p>
            <p>But to what hath been ſaid, ye will object and ſay, Chriſt <hi>Mark</hi> 16 (bidding his Diſciples that going forth into all the world they ſhould <hi>Preach the Goſpel to every Creature, and he that believed and was baptized ſhould be ſaved, but he that believed not ſhould be damned</hi>) ſaid, <hi>and theſe ſigns ſhall follow them that believe, in my Name they ſhall caſt out Devils, they ſhall ſpeak with new tongues, they ſhall take up Serpents, and if they drink any deadly thing it ſhall not hurt them, they ſhall lay hands on the ſick and they ſhall be well, or recover;</hi> So that theſe are the notes or marks of a true Goſpel Miniſtry, and therefore none may call himſelf an Apoſtle or Miniſter of Chriſt except he can confirm his Miniſtry by ſome of theſe; or any call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the true Church, unleſs ſuch ſigns follow them, or are found amongſt them.</p>
            <p>Tis true, theſe things mentioned were ſigns whereby their Miniſtry was propagated and confirmed; for without the gift of tongues the Goſpel could not have been ſo readily declared throughout the Nations into which they were to go; nor without the other ſigns would they ſo readily have believed that which they had never heard of before, but it doth not
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:103574:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> therefore follow that every one who went forth in the Miniſtry had tongues or did <hi>caſt out Devils, heal the ſick,</hi> &amp;c. For if any one were then moved by the Spirit of the Lord to Preach but in one Language, even in his Mother tongue, he was as true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Miniſter of Chriſt to thoſe to whom he ſpake as thoſe were that ſpake to divers Nations; As <hi>Apollo,</hi> who we read not to have either ſpake with any new tongue, or ever to do a mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, yet having received Wiſdom and Power from on high, he was an eminent Miniſter of the Goſpel, and an inſtrument by whom the <hi>Corinthians</hi> believed, as <hi>Paul</hi> witneſſed; neither was alway a miracle wrought by thoſe who might ſometimes work ſuch a thing when People were converted, nay rather oftner by Preaching alone, without it; So the three thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand were converted by the Preaching of <hi>Peter</hi> without a miracle done at the time of their being pricked in heart, and gladly receiving his Word; ſo while <hi>Peter</hi> another time ſpake to <hi>Cornelius</hi> and his Family, the Holy Spirit fell on them, no miracle being wrought; ſo <hi>Paul</hi> Preached two whole years in his own hired houſe, having firſt declared the Truth to the <hi>Jews,</hi> ſome of whom believed the things that were ſpoken, and others believing not, and this without a miracle; So <hi>Lydia's</hi> heart was opened by <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Timotheus</hi> their ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, without a miracle; for ye muſt know that although ſuch things were ſigns when the Power was pleaſed ſo to operate, yet the living Word being declared by the living Power, was ſufficient enough (without any other ſign) to prevail, and approve thoſe ſo ſpeaking to be the Miniſters of Chriſt to whom they ſpake; ſo the <hi>Corinthians</hi> were the ſeal of <hi>Pauls</hi> Apoſtleſhip, his Goſpel coming to them in the Power and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of the Spirit; ſo were they his <hi>Epiſtle</hi> that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended his Miniſtry, known and read of all men. Know alſo that though God did then freely come forth in ſuch a way, yet thoſe who ſought a ſign were an Adulterous generation; for if a man would but believe and keep to the Word nigh in his mouth and heart when declared in him or unto him, he need not look out for any ſuch thing. And as for thoſe ſigns fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing thoſe who believed, it could not be all thoſe who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, for moſt of the believers or members of the true Church ſpake neither with tongues, or ſhewed any miracles, as is undeniably evident, neither could thoſe be Eſſential
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:103574:22"/> ſigns of Faith; for nothing is the proper token of that but works of righteouſneſs alone, as <hi>James</hi> witneſſeth, and none ever denyed; ſo then theſe ſigns following thoſe that believed, were indeed further confirmations that ſuch did believe wherein they appeared, while the Eſſential tokens thereof remained with them, but if they ſhould be abſent <hi>(as love which is the fulfilling of the Law)</hi> though any one ſhould ſpeak with the tongue of men and Angels, and have Faith ſo as to remove mountains, it would profit nothing, and ſo be no ſign of his being a believer. And ſo the falſe Prophets miracles which <hi>John</hi> ſaith he wrought before the Beaſt can be no ſign of his Faith or of a true Miniſtry, becauſe he is an enemy of all righteouſneſs. But to come more home to this point, I ſay, that as the Commiſſion was given to the Apoſtles and Saints to Miniſter in that age, till the Apoſtacie, according to the ſeveral gifts and operations of the Spirit, and the work they had then to do, which was a great deal in a little time, as going far and near; and as this Commiſſion was declared by Chriſts perſonal mouth before his departure, which was ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated in them, and fulfilled in that age; ſo in the ſecond reſtauration, Chriſt the light gives a ſecond Commiſſion by his Spirit, to thoſe who have waited in his light, what to Miniſter with, and how to Miniſter, according to their work in this his laſt day; which is firſt of all to unfold the skirts of the great and myſtical Whore, who will acknowledge Chriſt and the Scriptures in words, but oppoſe and betray his pure Life; wherefore he commandeth his wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>neſſes now to fight with her with the ſword of his mouth, in the Power of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, which is better then outward ſtrength, and ſo they act and ſpeak as he moveth and enableth them, keeping to their own gift, meaſure and work, as the Apoſtles and Saints formerly did to theirs; and not regarding how they acted or ſpake, ſo as to be moved or troubled at it, as to queſtion their call to the work of the Miniſtry; for they know if they receive the witneſs of man, the witneſs of God is greater, which witneſs is his light within them, which plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſheweth them and ſealeth in them (though the whole world gain-ſay it) that they have felt in themſelves the Baptiſm of the ſpirit and fire (whoſe effects I before declared) and ſo
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:103574:22"/> the operation of his living Word, which hath brought thouſands of others to believe in the ſame light, and many to feel alſo the ſame living Word and ſpiritual Baptiſm, which hath ſhaken the Earthly part within like a cottage; and alſo the outward body of ſome, putting words in their mouths to declare his righteouſneſs in the great Aſſembly, and magnifie his Holy Name in the Congregations of his Saints; this was that greater work that Chriſt ſaid his Diſciples ſhould do then he had done, becauſe he went to his Father, for the Spirit was not yet given becauſe Jeſus was not yet glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified, this is really witneſſed among us, the Spirit ſealing it in our hearts; ſo that we witneſing the one Lord, one Faith and one Baptiſm, we are thereby baptized into the one body, and being many are one bread, and ſo the true Church that is come and coming out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and out of the wilderneſs, Glory be to the Lord for ever, who hath thus viſited and Redeemed his People; for this living Power is the gift it ſelf, tongues, miracles, propheſie, &amp;c. are but the gifts flowing as ſtreams from this fountain; now if the Lord do keep back ſome ſtreams, and give us more of the fountain in this his day, we are not looſers but gainers by that, and ſo the more to be owned as the Church of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But ye will ſay, when the Church was brought out of myſtical <hi>Babylon, John</hi> declareth <hi>there was an Angel who flow thorow the midſt of heaven with an everlaſting Goſpel to Preach to them that dwell on the Earth, and to all Nations, kindreds, tongues, and People,</hi> which (ſince we ſee not how that could be without the gift of tongues) ſheweth us, that the true Miniſtry muſt have the very ſame viſible gifts now, as the Apoſtles had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they undertake to go forth.</p>
            <p>That People were never truely called out of <hi>Babylon</hi> before the Preaching of this everlaſting Goſpel, is certainly true, and that it is to be Preached to all ſorts of People upon the Earth, is as cer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>in; but that this Goſpel muſt not be Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſome till the gift of tongues be given, where by it might be declared to all, is falſe; for the Wiſdom of God teacheth his People in what manner and order he will proceed in the publiſhing his truth throughout the world, it muſt begin firſt, in <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Egypt,</hi> where our Lord, (Chriſt the light and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:103574:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> life) hath been crucified; I mean the Anti-chriſtian State, which under pretence of profeſſing Chriſt, oppoſeth him; this Beaſt indeed is many headed, and conſiſts of divers Nations, but they muſt not all be cut off at once, but by degrees; we know by experience (what ever ye believe) that he hath begun his work in this Iſle of the North, wherein we live, and that there have been wayes made ſomewhat to awaken other Nations alſo; the pure Language being known, a tongue hath not been wanting to ſpeak to them in; and in this one thing do I behold Gods great Wiſdom, that he hath taken the wiſe in their own craftineſs; that whereas the Antichriſtian Prieſts have (as the <hi>Hebrew</hi> and <hi>Greek</hi>) ſo eſpecially idolized the <hi>Latine</hi> or <hi>Romane</hi> tongue, all over <hi>Europe,</hi> whereby its become a general Language; hereby a good occaſion is given to ſpread the truth, throughout all theſe Nations of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, ſo called; alſo ſo much hath been the mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all commerce betwixt theſe Antichriſtian People for many years, as counting each other to be Chriſtians, that in any of theſe Nations it may be either ſpoken in their own Language, or by an Interpreter: which laſt way is not to be deſpiſed; for the mighty God brings and will bring to paſs great things in theſe laſt times by weak beginnings, and none is to deſpiſe the Day of ſmall things; yea, the voice hath been hard in <hi>Turkie</hi> already: and if any of you ſhall ſay, But what had they to do to go thither, without the gift of the Tongue? I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, you muſt ask him that moved them thereto, even by tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in to Gods witneſs which is his true light within every one of you, and waiting there for Counſel, ye ſhall know the Lords ſecrets, and feel his Power to ariſe, which ſhall bring you into Unity with their Spirits, who knew their Call, which ye will not then diſpute; but in the mean time, him that is ignorant, let him be ignorant; but however know, that your unbelief cannot make the truth of God of none effect. But is it not Propheſied by <hi>Iſaiah</hi> concerning the Church, that he will turn his hand upon her, and p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rely purge away her droſs, and take away all her tin, and will reſtore all her Judges as at the firſt, and her Counſellors as at the beginning, afterwards ſhe ſhall be called the City of Righteouſneſs, the faithful City: Zion ſhall be Redeemed
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:103574:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> with Judgement, and her converts with Righteouſneſs; whereby it appeareth that at the Reſtauration of the Church the ſecond time (which is a very refining time, and of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption through Judgement and Righteouſneſs which ye talk ſo much of) the Miniſtry of the Church ſhall be as they were at the firſt gathering of it by the Apoſtles, and ſo gifted juſt as they were.</p>
            <p>The endowing of the witneſſes at their Reſurrection, ſhall be with the Spirit of life from God entring into them, and ſo they ſhall be as at the firſt; for that is the gift it ſelf, which brings into Unity of Spirit all the Prophets, Apoſtles and Saints in all ages, and into Unity in Miniſtry, as declaring one Everlaſting Truth for ſubſtance, and from one Eternal Root; but in reſpect of the gifts and operations of that one Spirit or Gift, it may be different at ſundry times and ſeaſons, according to the work that is to be done and the various work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the Spirit it ſelf; So God who at ſundry times and divers manners ſpake to the Jews by the Prophets, ſpake in the laſt times by his Son, by whom alſo he ſpeaketh ſundry wayes, at ſundry times, though not a ſundry truth; for the Apoſtles bare witneſs to the true light that lightneth every man, and to the Word nigh in the mouth and heart, as <hi>Moſes</hi> alſo witneſſed; and ſo do we now by the ſame Spirit: they were for taking up and ſtanding in the Croſs, fulfilling of all Righteouſneſs, and for ſeparation from every Idol, and all Idolatrous wayes, and ſo are we now, and that not only in word, but in deed and in truth: they would not go forth to ſpeak and ſuffer in their own ſtrength without power from above felt to enable them thereunto, neither dare we the like without the ſame Power; ſo then here are now Judges as at the firſt, the ſame Spirit of Judgment proceeding (yea, the Lord in his People rather com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more near to Judgement) and Counſellours as at the beginning, thoſe that exhort and reprove in the ſame Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, whoſe words the earthly mind is even leſs able to bear than formerly, for Plagues and Woes unſufferable: and ſo ſcorching vials are now pouring forth upon the ſeat of the Beaſt and the Whore, and hail-ſtones fall from Heaven upon the wicked like the weight of a talent; and thoſe who ſpeak in all wiſdom to the Saints themſelves, are ſeen, ſo miniſtring from the life to the ſame immortal life, whereby they are built
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:103574:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> up unto a perfect man; ſo that neither are they to be denied to be Counſellours as at the beginning, becauſe they do not exhort People to be Baptized with water, &amp;c. for they find not that in their ſpiritual Commiſſion; yea, ſee by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal light, the end of all ſhadows which muſt and do flee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way at the very dawning of this bright day of the coming of the Son of man, which ſhall never ſet more; for ſaith the Lord to the Church, <hi>Thy Sun ſhall no more go down at noon:</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe it ſhall, but not decreaſe; So here now is the true Tryal of the true Church and Miniſtry, when the ſign of the Son of man is ſeen in Heaven, even himſelf appearing in his People as a univerſal light, enlightning every one as the light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning which ſhineth from one end of Heaven to the other: as alſo by the Baptiſm of Fire and the Holy Spirit, which is felt really amongſt us; for as <hi>Eliah</hi> (in <hi>Jezabels</hi> time) ſaid (when there was a conteſt about his being a true Prophet, or whether <hi>Baals</hi> prophets (who were 450) were ſuch or no) he that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth by fire let him be God; ſo the Lord anſwering <hi>Eliah</hi> by fire (a lively figure of this ſpiritual Baptiſm) it licked up the water which was in the ditch and wood, and fleſhly offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring (a true repreſentation of the conſuming outward ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, &amp; the hay, wood and ſtubble that <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh of) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he alone was known to be the Lords own Prophet, and the other (though many) to be falſe ones, and ſo he had domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion over them and ſlew them; So ſay I now to all Sects and Gatherings and Opinions in the world, where the Lord God Baptizeth with fire, conſuming and burning up the droſs, fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling his People that wait on him, with a Holy Jealouſie for his Holy Name, and againſt all evil in thought, word and deed, where the outward earthly tabernacle (as well as the inward) is ſhaken, where all ſhadows are made to vaniſh, as needleſs in ſuch a day as this, there is the true Church viſible, and the true Prophets and Witneſſes who ſlay all falſe prophets with the Sword of Chriſts mouth, laying them by ſpiritual Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) under Eternal Condemnation (they repenting not) and ſo caſting them into the lake of fire. And in this ſenſe is that place in <hi>Jer.</hi> 30. to be underſtood (which I believe ye (called <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ekers</hi>) much ſtick at) where the Prophet fore-telling the Reſtauration of the Church after the captivity, ſaid,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:103574:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>The City ſhould be builded upon her own Heap, and the Palace re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main after the manner thereof, and that their Children ſhould be as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foretime, and their Congregation be eſtabliſhed before the Lord, and their Nobles ſhould be of themſelves, and their Governour proceed from the midſt of them,</hi> &amp;c. to wit, by the building the Church upon the ſame true Foundation as formerly, even Chriſt the true light, and beſtowing on it the ſame ſpiritual gift, which was the Spirit of truth, the Fathers Promiſe to all true believers; So eſtabliſhing them upon the Rock of ages, againſt which the Gates of Hell ſhall not prevail; out of whom ſhould go forth ſuch Miniſters who ſhould be Noble and Valiant for the Truth, Chriſt himſelf, the Head of the Church, being their Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; who from the midſt of them ariſeth in his ſtrength to ſcatter all their enemies, and to puniſh all that oppreſſe them, as the Lord hath ſaid (he will do) by the ſame Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet; ſo that the Palace remains after the manner of the former, as enjoying the ſubſtance, though the ſhadowes and ſame gifts in all things be not practiſed by the Saints, or found amongſt them; for the Prophet <hi>Amos</hi> Chap. 9. fore-telling of the raiſing up of the Tabernacle of <hi>Dav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d</hi> that was fallen down, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſaid, <hi>That the Lord would build it as in the dayes of old;</hi> Now we find that the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> in <hi>Acts</hi> 15. ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plieth this Propheſie to the raiſing up of the Gentile Church in thoſe dayes; which was truly applied thereunto, becauſe (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Jewiſh Church of old was very far different, both in matter and manner of Adminiſtration, from the Churches of Chriſt then) yet it was builded as in the dayes of old, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was eſtabliſhed upon the Foundation of <hi>Abraham,</hi> with whom the Covenant was made both to the carnal and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ſeed, and becauſe the ſubſtance was felt and witneſſed, which was the ſame in the Saints in all ages. Wherefore I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort ye all (called <hi>Seekers</hi>) if ye will find what ye ſay ye ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to come to the light in your own ſelves, and wait low in it, ſo ſhall you find the vail to remove from off your under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, whereby the true &amp; faithful witneſs Chriſt Jeſus will be ſeen to ſtand up; and ſo all impediments &amp; ſtumbling blocks taken up from the Letter without will be removed, and a right underſtanding of the Scriptures be given, ſo as to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern of the times and ſeaſons; but ye muſt firſt come to the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:103574:25"/> Croſs by owning your Reprover for ſin, and deny the pride, pleaſures, intereſts, folly and vanities of this world, ſo as not the longer ye ſeek, the worſe ye grow (as 'tis too manifeſt ſome of you have done) for it is the humble that he will teach, and his ſecret is with them that fear him, ſo as to ſhew them his Covenant (for ſo have I found it by experience) which Covenant of light being witneſſed, ye will eaſily ſee your way to <hi>Sion,</hi> and your Leader thither, not ſtanding ſtill for lack of gifts in others, or wanting an Adminiſtrator of external ordinances, but will keep to your own, and find in due time ſuch pure Power to ariſe, as will adminiſter to you in his own Sanctuary, and make you Miniſter that to others, which will plainly ſhew that ye are thoſe who are called &amp; choſen &amp; faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, though ye never ſpeak with any other Tongue than your Mother Tongue, or do any outward Miracle; yet ſpeaking and declaring of all his wonderful works.</p>
            <p>Now come I to ſtand up in defence of the Truth and true Church of the firſt born, againſt all you of what ſort ſoever you be, or under what name ſoever ye go who being out of all thoſe aforenamed Sects, lift your heads on high, ſnuffing up the wind, and think it too low a condition for you to believe in the true light within you, which ſecretly reproveth for all ſin and evil, and ſo to wait humbly and ſilently therein, with the People of God (called <hi>Quakers</hi> in deriſion, becauſe they tremble at the Word of the Lord, and are afraid to offend (in the leaſt thing) that of God in them) for ſo muſt you much deny your ſelves, both in wiſdom, talking and behaviour amongſt men with whom ye converſe, which Croſs would to them ſeem a ridiculous and fooliſh thing in you: Ye will ſay perhaps ye are above Ordinances or ſhadows, and can live ſatisfied of your ſelves by that which ye know and are taught of God, without joyning to, or walking with any; But con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider Friends, there is one great Ordinance which ye muſt never get above, but be in ſubjection to, if ever ye will have true Peace with the living God, and that is Chriſt the true light, who ſhines in every ones heart, either as a Juſtifier or Condemner, who is the great gift of the Father to the Sons of men, and him whom he hath ordained to ſave or deſtroy for ever. Now (whatever men may talk or tattle, or boaſt
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:103574:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> of themſelves) this is a more certain truth, ſealed in me by the Spirit of the Lord God, that whoſoever he be that truly believeth in Chriſt the light, doth whatſoever the light lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth unto, and that one ſpecial thing which it leads un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, is to bring the Creature, Soul, Body and Spirit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a right frame and order, out of its own will into the Will of its guide, which is the light; ſo as that man ſhall not walk at random, ſpeak or do as it pleaſeth him, but ſhall freely and naturally love the Society, and joyn viſibly in the bond of Amity with thoſe that believe and walk in the light, knowing a time of ſilence, as they do, and a bridle for the tongue, ſo as to keep his mouth as with a bit, and this is to walk in the foot-ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ps of the Flock; for in this manner doth the good ſhepherd put his ſheep forth, &amp; go before them in this his day, the ſtates and conditions of all thoſe who have been in ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual captivity, ſo requiring it; nor is it enough for any of you to ſay, is God tied up to a Form? For we know this is no form or frame of mans deviſing, but what the light na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally and mans condition neceſſarily calls him into; for if his delight be with the Saints and thoſe that excel in vertue, as <hi>Davids</hi> was who had a ſincere heart, he cannot but come amongſt them in love, and if they there wait on the Lord, he to wait with them, if they ſeek the Lord, he to ſeek him with them, if they love the Lords Judgements and Reproofs, he to love them alſo, and if they rejoyce in the Lord, he to rejoyce alſo; this is to be like minded and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionate one to another, hereby doth the pure and unfeigned love appear, &amp; the Unity or the Onety in the Spirit is witneſſed, here is a Church viſible in a ſweet and ſpiritual order, and yet out of any invented or humane form; for although we know and ſay that mans order is confuſion, yet we alſo know and ſay that God is a God of order not of confuſion; Now what is more comely than for Friends and Brethren in the truth to live together in Unity, and in what way can this Unity be more ſhewen, than by meeting and aſſembling toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to wait upon the Lord, to know his Counſel, to feel his Teachings, to ſpeak when he ſpeaketh, to move when he mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth, and to reſt when he reſteth; Is not this Gods way of leading his People to <hi>Canaan,</hi> yea, and in <hi>Canaan,</hi> is not this one part of walking in the light of the Lamb, is not this a part
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:103574:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> of that one heart and one way that the Lord hath promiſed to lead his People in? is not here a ſpiritual Harmony, and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, doth not the Saints (in a great meaſure) appear to be a City ſet on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Hill that cannot be hid? Let that of God anſwer in every one of you, and not your own high concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings.</p>
            <p>But ye will be ready to ſay, <hi>What difference is there betwixt you and other Sects in this? they meet together</hi> (as you do) <hi>in an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed place, and at a ſet hour, they pray, ſit and hear one ſpeak to them,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and you do the like.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doth not right reaſon (unleſs any be paſt reaſon) tell you, that if Perſons meet they muſt have a Place to meet at or in, and that they muſt alſo know the time of their ſo aſſembling, why then do you argue againſt neceſſity it ſelf? But if the end of your ſo objecting be to deſtroy all general Aſſemblings of the Saints together, then I ſay you ſpeak not in Gods Wiſdom, nor know not the thoughts of his heart; for the Apoſtle who was in the Wiſdom of God, and had received the Spirit of Truth to guide him, ſaith, <hi>Exhort ye one another daily, leaſt any of you be hardned through the deceitfulneſs of ſin;</hi> and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as perhaps ye may think ſuch Meetings are needleſs, becauſe of this day of the Lord that is riſen and ariſing; the ſame Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle argues quite contrary, ſaying, <hi>Not forſaking the Aſſembling of your ſelves together</hi> (as the manner of ſome is) <hi>but exhorting one another, and ſo much the more, as ye ſee the day approaching;</hi> Oh! People conſider, that the perfect day of the Lord is moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding deſirable of all the Children of light; therefore the more they eſpy it, the more they ſeek after it; Now Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations or other Declarations that come from the light of life, raiſeth the light of life in others, and ſo brings on the day; for it is like fire begetting fire, or like face anſwering to face in a glaſs, not like the dead and dry words of other Aſſemblies, where there is no waiting in the light (firſt) to feel the life, but a continual trading and going on in ſelf-ſtrength; but ye cannot nor dare not deny but that we do ſo wait, and all words ſpoken out of that are judged by the ſame: and if any one among us look out after words, and is not as well ſatisfied without them as with them, if the Lord will have all fleſh keep ſilence before him, that diſſatisfaction is Judged alſo. Beſides, if ye were in that which giveth a right diſcerning, ye
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:103574:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> would ſee that words ſpoken from the life are altogether <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for the conjviction and converſion of the world, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting their minds to the true light their guide; and would alſo ſee that moſt words that are ſpoken are for their ſakes, as taking compaſſion on the multitude, who are wandring like ſheep without a ſhepherd; and the Lord God will have all this ſo to be for <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> ſake, which he will make the praiſe of the whole earth; therefore ſhall not his Watch-men keep ſilence night nor day till her brightneſs go forth as the light, and her Righteouſneſs as the Lamp that burneth; Wherefore if ye knew what this meaneth, ye would not condemn the guiltleſs, yea, the faithful for doing their duty, for which they ſo ſuffer by the hands of wicked men; but it is no wonder that ye do ſo, for ye being in a too looſe liberty, under pretence of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Liberty, deſpiſe and ſhun the Croſs as fooliſhneſs, which to us is the Power of God.</p>
            <p>But perhaps ye will further ſay, <hi>Although words may be uſeful to the world, as alſo to build up thoſe who are weak, or that are not come to perfection; yet to thoſe who have attained, they are uſeleſs, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thy own Doctrine, who haſt ſaid before that the Holy City had no need of the Sun, Moon or light of a Candle,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>'Tis one thing to hear words that come from the life out of neceſſity, and another thing to hear them in the Unity; now the Saints who walk in the Lambs immediate light alone, may hear the Bride-grooms voice in others, and have great joy therein, though they are not ſpoken to their particular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, or have no need at all of any outward Declaration to build them up; ſo <hi>John</hi> his joy was fulfilled, in hearing what Chriſt preached to others; Therefore the Aſſembly of all Saints is ſtill needful, both to rejoyce together in the Truth, and to witneſs the ſame in the ſight of others.</p>
            <p>But ſome of you may ſay, <hi>Though we are not of the number of any of thoſe Sects thou haſt mentioned, nor walk with you (yet we do meet together at certain times) and pray and preach; yea, and ſing alſo (and are therefore called the ſinging People) and profeſſing the Virgin life, as thoſe who live in the higheſt Region of Light and Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Friends, conſider ſeriouſly with your ſelves what you do, leaſt ye deceive your own Souls; for it is not in words, no nor the higheſt words that can be uttered (nor thoſe in the higheſt
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:103574:27"/> manner) that Gods Kingdom doth conſiſt; therefore examine your ſelves whether ye are yet come to the firſt Principle of God in your ſelves, which is the true light within, that ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the heart, judgeth the deceit thereof, makes humble and meek, pulls down pride within and without, roots out the covetouſneſs, denies reſpect of or from perſons, brings to the Croſs every way, &amp; into the true ſilence, before the mouth is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened by the Power; for who ſhall take his Word or Covenant into his mouth, that is not Reformed? Or how can the dead praiſe the living? Now thoſe marks of Non-reformation by the light, are too viſible upon you; Wherefore ſtop your mouths ye Preaching &amp; Praying lumenaries that are found in the pollutions of the world, that flee the Croſs, and love not to come to the light that ye may be Judged; but will be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to be angry or touchy at ſuch words as theſe, ſaying, <hi>We are too cenſorious, or the like;</hi> when as they are but the words of truth and ſoberneſs, for truth and ſobriety conſiſts in plain dealing, which ye all will confeſs is a Jewel, and yet do not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be plainly dealt withal; ye are they that cauſe diviſions &amp; rents, profeſſing to be taught of God, &amp; yet ſtand at a diſtance from thoſe who by his true Teachings take up the Croſs and ſtand in it; Wherefore ſink down I charge you all ſuch, and come to the light, believing and waiting in it with us, and let not the glory of this world, or any other intereſt, pleaſure or luſt hinder you from ſo doing, ſo ſhall ye be called the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairers of the breaches, and thoſe that follow Love and Peace aright, which is ſhewen in nothing more than by ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving one heart and one way with Gods People (who ye will not deny many of us to be) to ſerve him (with them) with one conſent; for we know that ye ought to return to us, and that we muſt not return to you.</p>
            <p>And as for you <hi>Singers,</hi> conſider whether ye have not rather cauſe to mourn and lament, ſince thoſe things which are the proper cauſes of ſorrow are found in and among you? Will ye be covetous, proud and lofty, ſelf-ſeeking, diſſemble for advantage ſake, reſpect and court perſons, and the like, and come before the Lord with a Song? Can ſuch ſing the New Song as Redeemed from the earth? Nay, they that live in pleaſure are dead while they live, and ſo are in the grave of ſin, in which there is no true remembrance of the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:103574:27" rendition="simple:additions"/> Lord God of Life and Power, and far from the undefiled Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginity of the Lambs Wife. Wherefore be not deceived, God is not mocked, for this is but a mockery, and except ye come firſt to the houſe of mourning, and bid Adieu to all your lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, and paſs under the Rod, ye cannot be brought into the bond of the Covenant of Light, Life and Peace, but your Harps muſt needs be (ere long) hanged upon the Willowes; For how ſhould ye ſing the Song of the Lord in a ſtrange Land?</p>
            <p>But I hear ſome of you retorting, and ſaying, <hi>Thou haſt judged all but your ſelves, as living in ſin, and divers luſts and ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, &amp;c. but we ſee the ſame things among you, that thou chargeſt us with and denieſt us for; Is not covetouſneſs idolatry, and unmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifulneſs a fruit of unrighteouſneſs? are not ſome of you alſo in the pride in your houſe, and in the fulneſſe of bread, when ſome are pinched? are ye not too partial in looking upon one more than a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother? doth not anger and emulation and judging one another wrongfully, and raſh ſpeaking appear among you? do we not ſee theſe things, and why then ſhould ye be accounted more the Church of Chriſt than any other People; for the Kingdom of God ſtands not in yea and nay, pulling or not pulling off a hat, ſaying thou to any one, or wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of apparel, or taking by the hand, but in Righteouſneſſe and all the fruits thereof, as thou thy ſelf haſt ſaid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If I ſpeak of my ſelf my witneſs is not true, I judge you not out of that light which judgeth all things, which ye ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther call natural and inſufficient, or ſleight as a little, low and weak thing, and ſo are out of that which ſhould make all works acceptable to the Lord, and which ſhould diſcover and deſtroy all unri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ouſneſs; ſo that ye are not only denied be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of your b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> fruits, but as being out from that which would make you bring forth good fruits, for make the tree good, and the fruit ſhall be good, ſaith Chriſt the light, in whom the tree is made good, as acting from a living Principle, yet that the tree is known by its fruit I grant and affirm and have affirmed againſt all looſe and ranting ſpirits in the world, who would have no outward action to be a mark or token of the good or evil tree; but the light, Life or Principle muſt not be ſeperated from the action, nor the action from it, for if ſo, all a mans righteouſneſs becomes unrighteouſneſs, as
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:103574:28" rendition="simple:additions"/> acted from ſelf, in the wrong ground, and his knowledge like a cloud without water. But as for your objecting againſt our converſation in the world; I ſay, we judge our ſelves (firſt) and eſpie the beam in our own eye; for being turned to the light which makes manifeſt, the leaſt thing that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth in us contrary thereto, is as a beam, which (while ſtanding) clouds and overſpreads the pure preſence of God; wherefore we are not at reſt day or night, till the beam be be plucked out, and ſo do we eſpie and reprove the faults of others who either plead for ſin as long as they live, or excuſe their own iniquity by others failings, and yet think themſelves ſafe. And this I would have none of you be ignorant of, that although we believe perfection to be attainable in this world, yet we are very ſenſible, that it is not the work of a day, moneth, or year, but that there muſt be much waiting, many a ſigh and groan, a great ſpiritual combate with the Dragon and his Angels within, a diligent and expert exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing of the whole Armour of light, ere ſuch a State be wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed; but this is our comfort, that we are truely turned to that which gives the victory in the end, and ſo are not faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs but believe, as alſo, that the Lambs War is truely begun in us, who fights our battels for us, while we ſtand ſtill and behold his Salvation; with which Salvation, ſome are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſaved, and others ſaving; ſo every one in his own meaſure and order, ſo that (in few words) if any or all of thoſe things by you objected ſhould ſometime appear in or among ſome of us, yet know they are not ours, but the evil ones to whom they belong; for when we ſpeak of our ſelves as Saints, we mind that which is born of God which cannot ſin, for that is the Elect Seed, which is for ever joyned to the Lord, and takes his part againſt the tranſgreſſour; and this I will ſay, not onely for my ſelf, but in the behalf of other brethren and friends (in whoſe defence I have been moved to make this Apologie) that there is never a one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, who are truely and ſincerely come to the light, but do love judgement, yea wait for his judgements to be brought to light, and forth to victory, even as the watchman watcheth for the morning; and ſo far are any ſuch from plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for any one ſin in thought word or deed, that it is their
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:103574:28" rendition="simple:additions"/> meat and drink to do the will of the Father; and like gall and wormwood to the pure thing of God in them, when it is not fulfilled, neither can they be (in the leaſt) content to ſhrowd themſelves under a Profeſſion of truth, ſo as the more freely to act deceit thereby, but both deſire and witneſs a growth in truth and righteouſneſs, as knowing that not to go forward is to go backward; And as for any that come amongſt us, and ſeem to walk with us, that are otherwiſe minded and conditioned then I have declared, by the light they are judged, and by the truth denied, and by the fan winnowed, and in themſelves condemned; wherefore ſtumble not at the light and truth becauſe of offences, for that cauſeth not the offence, but by degrees gathereth all things that do offend out of the Fathers Kingdom, and maketh fearfulneſs in due time to ſurpriſe the Hypocrite; ſo God is glorified, and his truth vindicated thereby. Thus the foundation of God ſtandeth ſure to the Seed, notwithſtanding all ſuch ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections, and the true Church which is the pillar and ground of truth is appeared in this our day, ſo that none hath any more juſt cauſe to diſown it for ſome faults and failings that may yet be found among us, then the heathen had juſt cauſe to deny the <hi>Jews</hi> outward, to be the Lords people, when they came out of <hi>Babylon</hi> to build the Temple, becauſe of ſome things that were not right and comely amongſt them, againſt which <hi>Nehemiah</hi> conteſted, and which were alſo rectified, which was a figure of Chriſt Jeſus the ſpiritual King, the Rectifier, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>former and perfecter of his People.</p>
            <p>And as for ſome outward geſtures and behaviour among men, which ye account as trivial and indifferent things, know that though they are little in themſelves, yet as they flow from a pure Principle of God in us, which makes us out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly to teſtifie againſt the pride and loftineſs of man, which is to be brought down in this the day of the Lords exaltation, they are of great and neceſſary uſe, and as for taking by the hand, it is a manifeſtation of equality and unity among friends in the life, and to be done from a pure moving, and not from a tie or cuſtome; but as for yea and nay, whatever is more either in word or work cometh of evil; And ſo I ſhall conclude with prayer to the God of all Grace, that as he
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:103574:29"/> which hath called us by his Son, is holy, ſo we may be holy in all manner of converſation more and more, till every thing that offendeth within or without be taken away, that ſo the <hi>new Heavens and new Earth, wherein dwelleth all righteouſneſs, may be enjoyed,</hi> wherein love (which the fulfilling thereof) doth plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully flow and not wax cold, that the Lord God may be glorified in us and we in him, and his Name be written in our fore-heads, to the ſtopping of the mouths of all that op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the truth, to him be praiſe, and glory and everlaſting Dominion now and for evermore.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:103574:29"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
